<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Collections of acute diseases The second and third part. The second part, contains all that the learn'd and experienc'd Dr. Sydenham, has written of the pestilential fever, and dreadful plague at London in the years 1665, 1666. The third part, collected from the same author, treats of the depuratory fever of the years 1661, 62, 63, 64. and of the new fever; together with an exact description of that wonderful convulsion, called chorea sancti viti, and of its cure: and of the cure of the fever that afflicts children upon breeding teeth, as also of the hectic fever that is peculiar to them.</title>
            <title>Collections of acute diseases. Parts 2 and 3</title>
            <author>Pechey, John, 1655-1716.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 182 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 58 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90344</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1020A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230079</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895907</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895907</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153471</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90344)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153471)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2366:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Collections of acute diseases The second and third part. The second part, contains all that the learn'd and experienc'd Dr. Sydenham, has written of the pestilential fever, and dreadful plague at London in the years 1665, 1666. The third part, collected from the same author, treats of the depuratory fever of the years 1661, 62, 63, 64. and of the new fever; together with an exact description of that wonderful convulsion, called chorea sancti viti, and of its cure: and of the cure of the fever that afflicts children upon breeding teeth, as also of the hectic fever that is peculiar to them.</title>
                  <title>Collections of acute diseases. Parts 2 and 3</title>
                  <author>Pechey, John, 1655-1716.</author>
                  <author>Sydenham, Thomas, 1624-1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 100, [8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J.R. and are to be sold by H. Bonwicke, at the Red Lyon in St. Paul's Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By John Pechey. - Wing.</note>
                  <note>Identified as Wing P1020A, reel 2366, of the UMI microfilm set "Early English books 1641-1700".</note>
                  <note>Cf. Wing P1020A which has "Henry Bonwick" in the imprint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C..</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Diseases --  Causes and theories of causation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Fever --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Plague --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153471:1"/>
            <p>COLLECTIONS OF <hi>Acute Diſeaſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Second and Third Part.</p>
            <p>The Second Part, Contains all that the Learn'd and Experienc'd Dr. <hi>Sydenham,</hi> has Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of the Peſtilential Fever, and dreadful Plague at <hi>London</hi> in the Years 1665, 1666.</p>
            <p>The Third Part, Collected from the ſame Author, Treats of the Depuratory Fever of the Years 1661, 62, 63, 64. and of the New Fever; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with an exact Deſcription of that won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Convulſion, called <hi>Chorea Sancti Viti,</hi> and of its Cure: And of the Cure of the Fever that afflicts Children upon breeding Teeth, as alſo of the Hectic Fever that is peculiar to them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>J. R.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>H. Bonwicke,</hi> at the <hi>Red Lyon</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:153471:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153471:2"/>
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>BY reaſon of many Avoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and other Impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the Publiſher has been much obſtructed, in carrying on the Work in Hand, but is now in ſuch a readineſs that he hopes to Publiſh the Fourth Part in a very ſhort time. It Treats of Agues, of a Pleuriſie, Peripneu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monia, Quinſey, Rheumatiſm, Dyſentery, Cholera Morbus, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:153471:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153471:3"/>
            <head>COLLECTIONS OF <hi>Acute Diſeaſes.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>The Second Part: <hi>Of the Plague, and other Peſtilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Fevers.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. I.</head>
                  <head type="sub">Of the Epidemic Conſtitution of the Year 1665. and 1666. at London.</head>
                  <p>THE foregoing Winter being extremely cold, and the Froſt <note place="margin">This Chapter is taken out of Dr. <hi>Syden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s Treatiſe of Acute Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes.</note> continuing without any Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion till Spring, it thaw'd ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly at the end of <hi>March</hi> in the year 1665. and <hi>Peripneumonia's, Pleuriſies, Quinſeys,</hi> and ſuch like inflammatory Diſeaſes, made great Slaughter of a ſudden. At the ſame time al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a continual <hi>Epidemic Fever</hi> ſhew'd it ſelf, 'twas
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:153471:4"/>
very different from the Genius of the continual Fevers that Reign'd in the preceding Conſtitution, of which ſcarce any us'd to invade at that time of the year. The Pain of the Head was more vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and the vomiting more ſevere, than in the former; and the <hi>Diarrhaea,</hi> which was moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly prevented in the other Fever, by taking a Vomit, was now heighthned by the ſame, and yet the Vomiting did not ceaſe. The external parts were dry as in the Fevers of the foregoing Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution; but after bleeding the Patient could ſweat, and the Symptoms were preſently mitigated by it; and this might be done at any time of the Diſeaſe; whereas in the former Fever you could neither attempt it ſafely, nor indeed could eaſily obtain your deſire, before the thirteenth or four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth day. The Bloud was like the Bloud of Pleutritics, and of thoſe that have a Rheumatiſm, only it had not ſo white a Jelly upon it: Theſe were at firſt the Diagnoſtic Phoenomena of this Diſeaſe; but in progreſs of the Year the Plague it ſelf broke out, accompanied with a great Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Pathognomonic Symptoms, as <hi>Carbuncles, Bubo's,</hi> and the like. It increas'd daily more and more, and came to its heighth about the Autumnal Aequinox, at which time it deſtroy'd about 8000 in the ſpace of a Week, notwithſtanding that two Thirds, at leaſt, of the Citizens betook themſelves to the Country for fear of Infection: Afterwards it began to decreaſe, and by reaſon of the cold of Winter almoſt ceas'd, only here and there one had it all the Winter, and towards the following Spring, at the approach of which it totally va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed; yet a <hi>Fever</hi> remained (tho not ſo Epede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mic)
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153471:4"/>
the whole following year, and even till the beginning of the Spring, 1667.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. II.</head>
                  <head type="sub">Of the Peſtilential Fever and Plague of the Years 1665, 1666.</head>
                  <p>I Have heretofore hinted by the by, that ſome Fevers are vulgarly accounted Malignant, whereas the extream violence of the Symptoms, which ſeems to countenance this Opinion, proceeds not from any venomous diſpoſition of the Diſeaſe, but from the ill Management of the Cure: For when we dont duly attend to the ſolution of the Diſeaſe deſtin'd by Nature, but raſhly begin ſome other Method, we mightily diſturb the Oeconomy of the whole Body, and turn all things topſie turvy: and on this Account the Diſeaſe, contrary to its wont, has a woful Aſpect, is different from its ſelf, and accompanied with irregular Symptoms; ſo that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it ſeems of another kind: But a <hi>Fever truly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant</hi> does not happen every day, and wholly differs from other kinds of Fevers, that are ſo call'd, by reaſon of the irregularities of the Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms; and is truly of the ſame Species with the Plague, only 'tis a degree below it; wherefore I will treat of the Riſe and Cure of both in the ſame Chapter.</p>
                  <p>That ſuch a diſpoſition, or texture, happens to the Maſs of Air, as occaſions various Diſeaſes at different times, is manifeſt to every one that but
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153471:5"/>
conſiders, that one and the ſame Diſeaſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys an infinit number of Men at ſome certain Seaſons, and at another time ſeizes only here and there a Man, and goes no further; and this is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry apparent in the Small-pox, eſpecially in the Plague, the Argument of this Chapter.</p>
                  <p>But what that diſpoſition of the Air is, from whence this Morbific Furniture proceeds, we know not; nor many other things about which the doat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and arrogant crowd of Philoſophers trifle: What-ever it be, upon this account at leaſt, the clemency and goodneſs of Almighty God is to be reverenced, becauſe peſtilential conſtitutions of the Air, producing the Plague (the greateſt of all Miſeries, and moſt deſtructive to Mankind) ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domer happen, than thoſe that cauſe leſs deadly Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes: So that the Plague rarely rages violently in our <hi>Britain</hi> oftner than once in the ſpace of thirty or forty Years. Some here and there die of the Plague for ſome years after a notable Peſtilence; and its wont to go off gradually, by reaſon the peſtilential conſtitution of the Air continues ſtill in part, and yet is not wholly changed to another more wholſom; and therefore it ought to be accounted only as the Gleanings of the laſt Harveſt: And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the Fevers that reign a year or two after a dreadful Plague, are wont to be peſtilential for the ſame reaſon: And tho ſome have not the Tokens of the Plague, yet are they much of the ſame Nature, and require the like method of Cure, as we ſhall make appear hereafter.</p>
                  <p>But beſides the conſtitution of the Air, as a more common Cauſe, there ought to be alſo another Procatartic, to wit, the reception of the Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153471:5"/>
either immediately by accompanying ſome plaguy Perſon, or mediately tranſmitted by a Fomes from ſome other place; for elſe if it ſhould happen while there is ſuch a diſpoſition of the Air as we have mentioned, a dreadful Fire would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently be kindled by a ſmall Spark, and the whole Air through that tract of Earth would ſuddenly beinfected with the Plague, by reaſon of the Breath of the Sick, and Carcaſſes of the Dead; ſo that there would be no more need of a Fomes, or perſonal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercourſe to propagate this dreadful Diſeaſe, but the very Air, paſſing in with the Breath, would be able to deſtroy a Man of it ſelf, tho he were carefully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd from the infected, if he has a Body fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with Humours, diſpos'd to receive the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. This Diſeaſe, when 'tis only ſporadical, afflicts ſome few promiſcuouſly, at any time, the Infection being as it were handed from one to another. But when there is alſo an Epidemic Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Air, it begins between Spring and Summer, that being a Seaſon moſt fit to produce a Diſeaſe, whoſe Eſſence chiefly conſiſts of an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flammation,</hi> as we ſhall ſhew hereafter. Moreover it has its times of Increaſe, and Declination, like other kinds of natural things: It begins at the time we ſaid; as the Year increaſes, it ſpreads; and as that declines, it decreaſes, till at length the Winter has chang'd the Air into a Diatheſis, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to this Diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>For if the changes of the Seaſons of the Year have no power over this Diſeaſe, but the peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lential Seeds beeing untamable by any Alteration of the Air, are tranſmitted from one to another in a perpetual Series, it could not be, but that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153471:6"/>
when it has once entred into any popular City, it ſhould ſtill increaſe the Funerals more and more, till by a continued deſtruction no one at length would remain to whom it might impart its Infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But that the contrary often happens, is clear, from the number of the dead, which increas'd to ſome Thouſands in one Week in <hi>Auguſt,</hi> but mightily decreas'd at the latter end of <hi>November,</hi> and almoſt ceas'd. And yet I don't deny, but that it may be, and which alſo ſome Authors have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, that the Plague has broke out at other Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the year, but 'tis rare, neither is ſuch a Plague very raging; beſides I very much ſuſpect, that the diſpoſition of the Air, tho it be <hi>peſtilential,</hi> is not ſufficient of it ſelf to cauſe the Plague, but that being always in ſome place or other, its ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conveighed by a Fomes, or by the coming of ſome plaguy Perſon from an infected place to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and is not epidemical there, unleſs alſo the diſpoſition of the Air incline to it: For otherwiſe, I don't underſtand how it comes to paſs, that in the ſame tract of Heaven, when ſome one Town is grievouſly afflicted with the Plague, another not far diſtant, by warily prohibiting any Commerce with the infected place, ſhould keep clear of it; as not long a-go, when the Plague rag'd cruelly almoſt over all <hi>Italy,</hi> it was ſhut out of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of <hi>Tuſcany,</hi> by the Care and Prudence of the <hi>Great Duke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Its firſt approach is almoſt always accompanied with ſhaking and horror, like the Fits of intermit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Fevers, preſently violent Vomitings, a pain a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Region of the Heart as if'twere preſs'd, a burning Fever, with the uſual <hi>concourſe</hi> of Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153471:6"/>
perpetually moleſt the Sick, till either Death it ſelf, or a happy eruption of a <hi>Bubo,</hi> or <hi>Parotis,</hi> diſcharges the morbific matter, and ſo frees them from that deplorable condition. It does indeed now and then happen, but ſeldom, that it comes without any ſenſe of a Fever before, and ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly deſtroys Men. The <hi>Purple Spots,</hi> which are the Forerunners of preſent Death, breaking out, as they are about their Buſineſs; but this ſudden Death (which is to be noted) ſcarce ever hapens, but at the beginning of a dreadful Plague; and is never, when it remits, and is weakned, or in Years in which 'tis not epidemical. It ſometimes alſo happens that Tumours appear, when neither a Fever, nor any other grievous Symptom went before; but I imagin that ſome little ſhaking or horror, tho leſs perceptible, always precedes. They that are after this manner, may ſafely walk about the Streets at pleaſure, and do their Buſineſs, as if they were well, not regarding any Regimen.</p>
                  <p>As to the eſſence of this Diſeaſe, I dont pretend to define it exquiſitly, and perchance, he would ſeem as impertinent to wiſe Men, who ſhould ask me, what conſtitutes this, or that ſort of Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as I ſhould, if I ſhould ask him the ſame Queſtion, concerning a <hi>Horſe</hi> for inſtance, among Animals, or <hi>Betony</hi> among Plants: For Parent Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture accompliſhes the Generation of all things, which any time ſhe brings to Light from the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of Cauſes, by moſt certain Rules, only known to her ſelf, and hides their Eſſence, Quiddities, and conſtitutive Differences, in the greateſt obſcurity. Hence every Species of Diſeaſes, no leſs than of Animals, or Vegitables, is always allotted Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153471:7"/>
peculiar to it ſelf, and univocal, flowing from its Eſſence: And yet notwithſtanding, that Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion will not be very conſiderable, to wit, How we ſhould cure Diſeaſes, when we are ignorant of their Cauſes? For as much as the Cure of moſt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes is perform'd, not by the knowledge of the Cauſes, but by a convenient Method, approv'd by Experience. But to return to the buſineſs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are wont to deduce the Riſe of all ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Deſeaſes from a Fault of the firſt or ſecond Qualities (which we can only do by reaſon of our great ignorance of things) 'tis probable, that the Plague is a peculiar Fever, of its own kind, proceeding from an <hi>Inflammation</hi> of the moſt ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituous Particles of the Bloud, for as much as they ſeem moſt adequate to its moſt ſubtle Nature: If it exert the greateſt ſubtilty, with which 'tis en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow'd, it ſuddenly diſſipates the native Heat, and ſo kills the Patient, as is ſeen at the beginning, and ſtate of an Epidemical Conſtitution. The Corps of thoſe who are ſo ſuddenly deſtroyed, by the violence of this Diſeaſe, are every where dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figured with Purple Spots, the Fibres of the Bloud being broken in pieces, by reaſon of the violence of the inteſtine Conflict, and the frame of it wholly diſſolv'd: And this Tragedy may be acted by reaſon of the great ſubtilty of its Flame, even without any febrile ebullition of the Bloud, or ſenſe before of any other Sickneſs, otherwiſe than it moſt commonly happens, where the Morbific Cauſe is leſs ſubtile, and the Weapon more obtuſe with which it aſſaults Life; the manner of the difference may be thus bluntly repreſented: For Inſtance, If a Needle, or any other ſharp thing, be put under
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153471:7"/>
a Pillow, and forceably preſs'd, it does not lift it up, as ſome things of a duller point would, but perforats it. But this kind of ſudden Death ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom happens, and only, as we ſaid before, at the beginning, or increaſe of the Plague: For moſt commonly, as in other Fevers, ſhaking and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror firſt invades, and heat preſently ſucceeds, which continues till the inflamed Particles of the Bloud are baniſhed to the Emunctories, by the provident conduct of Nature, and there turn'd into Puſs, after the manner of common Phlegmons. If the Inflammation be more remiſs, its wont to produce thoſe Fevers which are commonly call'd peſtilenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, which often happen at the end of a peſtilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Conſtitution; and perhaps a year or two after, till that ſpecies of Fevers wholly diſappears.</p>
                  <p>In my opinion, that Inflammation which is call'd an <hi>Eriſypelas,</hi> is much like the Plague; for 'tis ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted by the beſt Phyſitians a continual Fever, ariſing from the thinner part of the Bloud, from which that Nature may free her ſelf, ſhe expels it to ſome external part of the Body, in which a Tumor, or rather broad red ſpots diſpers'd (for a very viſible Tumor does not often appear) ariſe, which they call an <hi>Eryſipelas;</hi> but the Fever goes off critically by this Tumor, after it has afflicted the Sick a day or two. And moreover, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, there is wont to be Pain in the Glandules of the Arm-pit, or Groin, as in the Plague; and it begins alſo almoſt like it, with Horror, and a febrile heat following it: So that they who have not had this Diſeaſe before, think they are ſeiz'd with the Plague, till at length it ſhews its ſelf in the Leg, or ſome other part: And indeed ſome
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153471:8"/>
Authors have imagin'd that there was ſomewhat of Malignity in this Diſtemper, and therefore have proceeded in the Cure with Sudorificks, and Alexipharmacs. This Flame ſoon goes out of its own accord, and does no further miſchief, when by means of the ebullition, the torrid particles of the Bloud are caſt out.</p>
                  <p>But the Plague far exceeds an <hi>Eryſipelas;</hi> for by reaſon of the great tenuity of its ſubſtance, 'tis fitted to paſs through the innermoſt receſſes of the Body like Lightning, and ſuddenly deſtroys the Spirits of the Bloud, and diſſolves its frame, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore oppreſs'd Nature can raiſe a febrile ebulliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the wonted means by which ſhe endeavours to remove whatever is offenſive to the Bloud.</p>
                  <p>If any one be diſſatisfied with my Opinion, to wit, that this Diſeaſe is occaſioned by an Inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, let him conſider, that not only the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of a Fever, but alſo many other things, favour this Opinion. For inſtance, the colour of the Bloud taken away, which is like that of Pleu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritics, and of thoſe that have a Rheumatiſm, the aduſt appearance of a <hi>Carbuncle,</hi> not unlike the impreſſion of an actual Cautery, the <hi>Buboes,</hi> which are as much inclin'd to an Inflammation as other Tumors of any other ſort, and they end in abceſſes, as moſt inflammations are want to do; and alſo the Seaſon of the year, in which an epidemic Plague moſt commonly breaks out, ſeems to confirm the ſame; for at the ſame time, <hi>viz.</hi> between Spring and Summer <hi>Pleuriſies, Quinſies,</hi> and other Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes that proceed from an Inflammation of the Bloud, are wont to be epidemical; and I never knew them more frequent than they were before
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153471:8"/>
the Riſe of the <hi>London Plague.</hi> But 'tis of no im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, that that very year ſo dreadful, by reaſon of the deſtruction of many thouſands, was otherwiſe moſt mild and healthy, and that all that eſcaped the Plague were better in health, and alſo that thoſe who recover'd of it were after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards freed from Cachexies, and other indiſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons uſually occaſioned by the reliques of former Diſeaſes. And moreover, that the <hi>impoſthumated Carbuncles</hi> (after the inflamed particles were car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried off with the matter) were eaſily cur'd by Chirurgical means, and thoſe too not very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſit.</p>
                  <p>But perhaps, ſome one will ask, How it comes to paſs, that hot Medicines, ſuch as are almoſt all <hi>Alexipharmacs,</hi> ſhould be us'd with good Succeſs, both as to the cure of the Plague, as alſo for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation from it, if it conſiſts of an Inflammati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? To whom I anſwer, That theſe things do good only by accident, to wit, by the benefit of Sweat that they produce, by which the inflamed particles of the Bloud are exterminated; but if they don't cauſe ſweat when they are taken, as it very often happens, the flame of the Bloud, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creas'd by their adventitious heat, ſoon proclaims openly the miſchief of them. In a word, as to preſervation, I know, that the uſe of hot <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotes</hi> is alſo every where commended, but with what ſucceſs is not yet prov'd: Indeed 'tis ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther probable, that Wine drunk too freely, and other ſtrong preſervatives taken daily at ſet hours have caſt many into this Diſeaſe, who otherwiſe might not have had it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:153471:9"/>
As to the <hi>Cure</hi> of theſe Fevers, the <hi>Curative in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dications</hi> are firſt to be minded, which in general, are ſo to be directed, that either, exactly follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the conduct of Nature, we aſſiſt her in exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minating the Diſeaſe; or not truſting to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod ſhe is wont to uſe in conquering this inteſtine enemy, we ſubſtitute by Art, in the room of it, a contrary and more ſafe. But perhaps ſome one will ſay, that the cure of the Plague may be well enough performed by Alexipharmacs, great numbers of which may be found in practical Authors: but tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly 'tis very diſputable, whether the help theſe Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines afford, don't rather proceed from their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt qualities, by which, procuring Sweat plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, they prepare a way at the ſame time, for the excluſion of the Morbific matter, than from a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain occult Virtue allotted them by Nature, to expel the Venom of the Peſtilential Malignity. Neither may we only doubt of theſe, but alſo of the Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipharmacs of other Diſeaſes, <hi>viz.</hi> Whether they don't relieve the Sick, rather by ſtirring up ſome Evacuation, than by a Specific Virtue; for inſtance, in the <hi>French Pox;</hi> he that objects, that <hi>Mercury</hi> and <hi>Sarſaparilla</hi> are Alexipharmacs; for the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom in that Diſeaſe, muſt produce ſome examples of Cures, in which That did ſometimes reſtore Health without Salivation or Stools, and this with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Sweat; which I believe will be very difficult for him to do: But it ſeems probable to me, that the peculiar Remedy, and proper Alexipharmac of the Plague, yet lyes hid in Natures Boſom; nor can it be taken thence, but only by a Mechanic Reaſon.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:153471:9"/>
But that we may a little more fully conſider the former intention, which requires, that we ſhould aſſiſt Nature after her own way and manner, in expelling the Morbific matter: 'tis to be noted, that in a true Plague, Nature performs her buſineſs by ſome <hi>abceſs</hi> breaking out in the Emunctories, and ſo the matter is caſt out, when ſhe does not err, of her own accord; nor is violently forc'd out of the way; but in the Fever we call Peſtilential, the ſame is perform'd by means of Sweat, through the whole ſuperficies of the Body. Whence we may learn, that according to the various ways and order, which Nature diſcovers in both Diſeaſes, a different method of Cure ought to be inſtituted; for if any one endeavours to expel the matter of a true Plague by Sweat, he proceeds in a method oppoſite to Nature's for as much as ſhe attempts to do it by Impoſthumes; and on the contrary, he that endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to eliminate the matter of a Peſtilential Fever, any other way than by Sweat, takes a courſe no way agreeable to her conduct and inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But in the true Plague, 'tis not yet known by what fit and certain kind of Remedies, the ejection of the Morbific matter, that is, the erup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Impoſthumes may be promoted. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſome one may imagine, that a corroborating Diet, and Cordials, may conduce to it; but truly, I ſhould very much doubt, leſt they ſhould increaſe the heat of the Patient, that is too much already. And as to Sweats, I am fully ſatisfied by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that they ſignifie nothing in this caſe, tho I don't deny, but that after great Sweats, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued for the ſpace of three or four hours, and then ſuddenly ſtopt, the tumor ſhews its ſelf; but
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153471:10"/>
I don't think, 'tis at all occaſion'd by the Sweat; for as much as, when 'tis at height, there appears no ſign of its eruption: when 'tis over indeed, it may follow, as it were by accident, to wit, when the Sweat has remov'd part of that burden, by which Nature was too much oppreſs'd, and the Body violently heated by Cordials, taken to raiſe it. But how fallacious and uncertain this ejection of the peccant matter, is by impoſthumes, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion'd by Sweat, the lamentable end of thoſe teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies, who have bin treated after this manner, of which ſcarce one in three, (to ſpeak within bounds) eſcape the danger of the Diſeaſe and Cure. But on the contrary, many on whom the Tumors broke out in the right manner, even when they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent on their buſineſs, and without any ſenſible hurt of any natural, vital, or animal faculty, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd in a ſhort time: except thoſe, who unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunately falling into the hands of a Quack, and compoſing themſelves to Sweat, by his Advice, tho they were very well in Body and Mind, began from that very time to grow worſe; and their ſickneſs increaſing, they ſufficiently demonſtrated the injury of this unlucky Counſel, by their own death. But the uncertain Judgment of this Diſeaſe by Tumors, is manifeſt; for that ſometimes a <hi>Bubo,</hi> which comes out at firſt laudably, and with remiſſion of the Symptoms, afterwards diſappears of a ſudden, and inſtead of it, <hi>Purple Spots,</hi> the certain tokens of Death ſucceed. The cauſe of the going in of the Tumour, ſeems of right to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to thoſe Sweats, which were deſign'd to promote its eruption; for as much as, they diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pated, other whither through the habit of the Body,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153471:10"/>
the chief part of the matter, which ſhould have ſerv'd to have kept up the Tumour. However it be, this at leaſt plainly appears, that by the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignity of Almighty God, certain ways of caſting out the Morbific matter, are appointed in other Diſeaſes: but for this Scourge of hainous Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, only a very uncertain one. And perchance, the Cauſe and Original of this great deſtruction, may be as properly deduc'd from hence, as from <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity;</hi> for in the Gout, and other Diſeaſes that have little ſuſpition of Malignity, the ſtriking in of the Morbific matter is full as deſtructive. From all which it manifeſtly follows, that the Phyſitian, who is oblig'd to follow exactly the conduct and inclination of Nature, ought here to renounce her guidance; the truth of which, becauſe few have hitherto ſufficiently underſtood, therefore the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe whom the Plague deſtroy'd, was not a little increas'd.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore, ſeeing 'tis not at all ſafe to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Foot-ſteps of Nature in exterminating this Diſeaſe, we muſt conſider, in the next place, by what means we may ſatisfie that intention, which we call the ſecond; namely, by inſtituting a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of this Diſeaſe, contrary to that of Nature, and this I think, can only be done by theſe two ways, <hi>viz.</hi> either by Bleeding, or Sweat. As to the firſt, I am very ſenſible, that Bleeding is much abhorr'd by moſt in this Diſeaſe; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing little concern'd at the prejudice of the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, I will fairly diſcourſe the Validity of the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in this Queſtion. And firſt I appeal to thoſe Phiſitians that continued in Town when the late Plague rag'd, whether they ever obſerv'd, that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153471:11"/>
large Bleeding, and often repeated, before any Tumour appear'd, was the cauſe of any ones Death that had the Plague: But 'tis no ſtrange thing, that bleeding ſparingly, or after the Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour is come out, ſhould be always hurtful; for when only a moderate quantity of Bloud is taken away, the adminiſtration of Affairs is forc'd out of Natures hand, who endeavour'd all ſhe could to cauſe a Tumour; and yet in the mean while another Method is not ſubſtituted, that is power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful enough to evacuate the morbific matter: And bleeding us'd, after the Tumour appears (for as much as it draws from the Circumference to the Centre) induces a motion quite contrary to that of Nature, which is from the Centre to the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference; and yet nothing is more commonly urg'd as a mighty Argument by thoſe of the contrary opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion againſt bleeding in general in this Diſeaſe, than the injuries of Phlebotomy, adminiſtred after this perverſe manner, as may be every where ſeen, in <hi>Diemerbroek,</hi> and other Writers of Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. As for my ſelf, I can't aſſent to their Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, till I underſtand what they anſwer to the Queſtion above propos'd: For very many Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, and thoſe of the beſt Note, have thought bleeding proper in the Plague; the chief of whom are <hi>Ludovicus Mercatus, Joannes Coſtaeus, Nicholaus Maſſa, Ludovicus Septalius, Trincavellius, Foreſtus, Mercurialis Altomarus, Paſchalius, Andernachus, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reda, Zacutus Lucitanus, Fonſeca,</hi> and others: But there is but one that I know, who places the whole buſineſs of the Cure in as large a bleeding as we require, to wit, <hi>Leonardus Botallus,</hi> one of the moſt famous Phiſitians of the former Age,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153471:11"/>
whom I will quote, leſt I ſhould be thought ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar in this Practice; <hi>In a word,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I think there is no Plague in which this</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>In his ſeventh Chapter,</hi> Of the Cure by bleeding.</note> 
                     <hi>may not be better, than all other remedies, ſo it be us'd opportunely, and in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient quantity, for I ſuppoſe 'tis found unprofitable ſometimes; for that either 'tis us'd too late, or leſs is taken away than ought to be, or an error is committed in the uſing of it both ways.</hi> And a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle afterwards, he adds, <hi>But in ſo great Timidity, and ſparing Phlebotomy, how can it be that any one ſhould judge exactly how much good or hurt it may do in the Plague? for if a Diſeaſe (for the Cure of which, the taking away of four pounds of blood was required, and but one pound be taken away) kill a man, it does not therefore deſtroy him becauſe he was blooded, but becauſe it was not done in a due manner nor perchance ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably; but ſlothful wicked villains always endeavour to put the fault on that, not for that it did hurt, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they baſely deſire to have it diſapprov'd by all: or if they don't do it wickedly they do it ignorantly, by a perverſe cuſtom; both certainly are pernicious, but that moſt of all.</hi> All which being about to confirm by experience, a little after he thus proceeds, <hi>Theſe things being noted, no rational man can well diſpraiſe bleeding in theſe Diſeaſes, but rather wonderfully com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend and extol it, and confidently uſe it, as a Divine help, which truly I have done for theſe fifteen years. Therefore in Peſtilential Diſeaſes, at the Seige of</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel, <hi>and four years ago at the Mountains of</hi> Hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nault, <hi>and for theſe two years at</hi> Paris, <hi>and the laſt year at</hi> Cambray, <hi>I found no remedy ſpeedier and ſafer in all my Patients (which were innumerable) than large and ſeaſonable bleeding.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:153471:12"/>
And afterwards he delivers ſome obſervations, which for brevity ſake I here omit, but will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late a very rare caſe, and ſutable to our purpoſe, of a buſineſs performed in <hi>England,</hi> many years ago. When among the other Calamities of the Civil War, that miſerably afflicted this our Coun-try, the Plague alſo rag'd in many places, it chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to be brought from another place, to the Caſtle of <hi>Dunſtar</hi> in <hi>Somerſet-ſhire:</hi> and ſome of the Souldiers dying ſuddenly, with an eruption of Spots, it ſeiz'd many others, at which time a Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon, that had been a great Traveller, was a common Souldier there, who humbly beſeech'd the Governour of the Caſtle to permit him to do all he could do for the relief of his fellow Souldiers, that were ſeiz'd with this dreadful Diſeaſe; and having obtain'd leave, he took away a prodigious quantity of Blood from every ſick Perſon, at the firſt approach of the Diſeaſe, before there was any ſign of a Tumour; he bleed them till they were even like to drop down, for he bled them all ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and in the open Air, neither had he any por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringer to meaſure the blood; afterwards he order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them to lye in their Tents, and though he gave no Medicine at all after bleeding, yet (which is very ſtrange) of thoſe very many, he treated af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner, not one died. Mr. <hi>Francis Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> gave me this account, who was then Governor of the Caſtle, and is indeed a Gentleman, and remarkably honeſt, and is now living, ſo that any one may be ſatisfied, that doubts the truth of it.</p>
                  <p>I will mention what I have obſerv'd worth note, concerning this thing, when I come to treat, of thoſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:153471:12"/>
few remarks, I made by my own experience, while the late <hi>London</hi> Plague rag'd.</p>
                  <p>But tho' in my Judgment I approve of this practice, and have experimentally found the utili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it long ago; yet the diſſipation of the Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lential ferment by Sweat pleaſes me better upon many accounts than the evacuation of it by bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: for as much as it does not weaken the patient ſo much, nor hazard the Phyſitians reputation: but this has alſo its inconveniencies; for firſt, many, eſpecially young Men, of a hot conſtitution, ſweat difficultly, and in ſuch the more you endeavour to cauſe Sweat by ſtrong Diaphoreticks, and by heap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on a great many Clothes, ſo much the more are they in danger of falling into a phrenſie; or what is yet worſe, after having been entertain'd a while with vain hopes, the <hi>Tokens</hi> are forc'd out inſtead of it. For the chief venom of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe reſiding in the moſt ſpirituous part of the bloud (the motion of the groſſer particles being on this account ſomewhat more languid, than is uſual in other inflammations) that tender portion is driven into a greater fury, by the acceſſion of this new heat, and at length violently breaks in pieces all the Fibers of the blood, diſtended beyond the bounds of their texture; which diſſolution of the ſanguineous Fibers, I take to be the cauſe of the Peſtilential Tokens. For, firſt, they are intenſly Red, and ſoon after Livid or Black, not unlike <hi>ſtripes</hi> inflicted by a violent blow on ſome muſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous part of the Body.</p>
                  <p>And then in thoſe bodies which are eaſie to ſweat, if it be ſtopt too ſoon, to wit, before the Morbific matter be wholly diſſipated, the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:153471:13"/>
of the Buboes is afterwards worſe, which began to come out well at the latter end of the ſweat. For that part of the matter being ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted, which ſhould ſerve to elevate them, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ſoon ſtrike in, or at leaſt never come to true abceſſes (as is wont to happen in the ſmall Pox, when the ſick has ſweat violently at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Diſeaſe) but the cruel Enemy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing again taken in, a commotion is ſtir'd up in the blood, by which means the <hi>Purple ſpots,</hi> the Tokens of ſuddain death are often driven out: in the manner we have deſcrib'd above.</p>
                  <p>But that it may be more clearly evident by what means we may obviate theſe and the like difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, I will faithfully ſet down what has been done and obſerv'd by me, ſo far as I was able, in this Diſeaſe, beginning from the riſe of the late Plague.</p>
                  <p>At the beginning of <hi>May,</hi> 1665. I viſited a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Lady, about one and twenty years of age, of a Sanguine complexion, beſides the burning Fever, which began a little before, frequent Vomitings and other Febrile ſymptoms moleſted her. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan the Cure with Phlebotomy, and the next day to prevent a Diarrhaea, (which as I noted at the beginning of this Treatiſe, was wont to come at the latter end of the Fever, when an Emetic was omitted, which the inclination to Vomiting at the beginning of the Diſeaſe requir'd) I order'd a Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit that carried off the filth of her ſtomach very well: The day after, viſiting her again, I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood ſhe had a Diarrhaea, which being very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſual for ſome years, did not a little perplex me; but from thence I gather'd that this was no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Fever, (as was alſo apparent from the event)
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:153471:13"/>
and therefore required another method of Cure, different from that I deliverd in another place, which I had us'd hitherto with continu'd ſucceſs. Wherefore another elder Phyſitian being call'd in to aſſiſt me, bleeding was repeated by our joint conſent; which the age and conſtitution of the Patient, and the inordinate ebullition of the blood ſeem'd to require; and alſo Cordials mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately cooling were preſcrib'd, and Clyſters were injected every other day. At the latter end of the Diſeaſe we order'd ſome of the ſtronger Alexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pharmacs, becauſe very unuſual and irregular ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptoms invaded, commonly reckon'd the ſigns of great Malignity: but all doing no good, ſhe dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about the fourteenth day. I had various thoughts for ſome days after, about the odd di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſition of this Fever; and at length remembring the violent heat which continued in the foreſaid patient, even after repeated bleeding, that there was a redneſs in the Cheeks, and that ſome drops of blood flow'd from her Noſtrils a little before her death, and that alſo the blood when 'twas cold in the porringers was not unlike that which is taken from Pleuritics; moreover that ſhe had a Cough, and certain obſcure pains in the vital parts: beſides that that ſeaſon of the year approach'd, which contains the end of Spring and beginning of Summer, and which is leſs diſpos'd for the production of continual Fevers, (for theſe of their own accord, at this time, either turn to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termittents, or ſuddenly change to Pleuriſies, or other inflammations of the like kind); and laſtly, that Pleuriſies at that very time were very Epide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical. All theſe things, I ſay, being duly weigh'd,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:153471:14"/>
I was of the opinion that this Fever, tho' 'twas deſtitute of the Pathognomonic ſigns of a Pleuriſie or Peripneumonia, had the importance of a Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptom, on the account of a certain Inflammation lurking about the vital parts, tho' there was no pain of the ſide, nor no conſiderable difficulty of breathing: To be ſhort, at length I was perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that I muſt wholly proceed, in the 'foreſaid caſe, with the ſame method which I had often us'd, with excellent ſucceſs, in a Pleuriſie; and indeed it afterwards ſucceeded as well as cou'd be wiſh'd: for being call'd a little while after to a Man that was ill exactly after the ſame manner I began and finiſh'd the Cure by repeated bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as is commended in a Pleuriſie. About the latter end of <hi>May</hi> and the beginning of <hi>June,</hi> very many, deſiring my aſſiſtance, were recover'd from this Fever (which was then very Epidemical) by the 'foreſaid method. From this time that dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Plague began to rage cruelly, which at length was ſo very mortal, that in the ſpace of ſeven days it deſtroy'd ſo many thouſands in this one City.</p>
                  <p>But whether the Fever, of which we have now Diſcours'd, deſerve the name of the Plague, I dare not confidently affirm: but this I know experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally, that all that were ſeiz'd with the true Plague at that time, and ſometime after in my Neighbourhood, with all the Symptoms peculiar to it, had the ſame concourſe of Symptoms both at the firſt coming of the Diſeaſe, and in the whole courſe of it. But when I was endanger'd by the near approach of the Plague to my own Houſe, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ngth, by the perſuaſion of Friends, I accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pani'd
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:153471:14"/>
the vaſt numbers of thoſe that left the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and remov'd my Family ſome Miles from thence; yet I return'd ſo very ſoon, and when the Plague continued ſo violent, that it cou'd not be, but by reaſon of the ſcarcity of better Phyſitians, I ſhou'd be call'd into the aſſiſtance of thoſe that had the Plague. And not long after I viſited ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that had Fevers, which I perceiv'd (not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great admiration) were like that I manag'd ſo ſucceſsfully before my departure; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore confiding in my own experience, as a guide to be prefer'd before all idle precepts, I did not doubt to order bleeding again. I continu'd this courſe of bleeding plentifully (together with the uſe of a Ptiſan and ſuch like cooling diet) in many Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, with very great advantage, till at length miſſing my wonted ſucceſs in the management of ſome, by reaſon of the frowardneſs of the ſtanders by; who being poſſeſs'd with vain prejudices, wou'd not permit me to take away a due quantity of blood (to the great damage of the ſick, from whom a ſufficient quantity or none at all ſhou'd have been taken away, ſeeing the ſtreſs of the Cure depended on it) I perceiv'd a great obſtruction to my deſigns, and therefore thought 'twould be of great uſe to find ſome other method of curing this Diſeaſe beſides that of bleeding. I will inſtance in an injury I once did (but without guilt) not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I let blood, but for that I was not permitted to take away ſo much as I deſir'd; being ſent for to a young Man of a ſanguine complexion and ſtrong conſtitution, whom a violent Fever had ſeiz'd two days before, with giddy pains of the Head, violent Vomitings and other ſuch Symptoms,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:153471:15"/>
and finding upon inquiry that he had no ſign of a Tumor, I preſently order'd that blood ſhould be taken away in a large quantity, the ſuperficies of which, when 'twas cold, repreſented the corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed blood of Pleuritics; and I preſcrib'd alſo a Pty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan with cooling Julaps and Broths; in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon he bled a ſecond time the ſame quantity, and likewiſe the next Morning, and towards the Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this day I viſited him, and found him much better; yet notwithſtanding I perceiv'd his friends violently oppos'd the taking away any more blood: but I earneſtly contended that it ſhou'd be again repeated, ſaying, he need be blooded but this time only, and then he wou'd be out of danger; but that if they ſhou'd continue obſtinate, it had been better that no blood had been taken away, and that the Cure had been carried on by ſweat, and in a word that the patient wou'd moſt certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dye: The event confirm'd the Prognoſtication, for while we were diſputing about the thing, we loſt the opportunity of doing it; for the next day the Purple ſpots broke out, <hi>viz.</hi> the reliques of the peccant matter which ought to have been wholly evacuated (for as much as Phlebotomy ſo often repeated had taken away all hopes of an Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs) by delay perverting the whole maſs of blood, and breaking the texture of it by its great ſubtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the Patient died in few hours. When therefore I had frequently met vvith ſuch obſtacles, I earneſtly endeavour'd to find out (if poſſible) ſome method of Cure, that might be as effectual and not ſo diſpleaſing: And having much and long deliberated the thing in my mind, at length I fell upon this method, which I found afterwards,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:153471:15"/>
to be perfect in all reſpects and always benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, If the Tumor has not yet ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd, <note place="margin">The Cure.</note> I bleed moderately with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the ſtrength and temperament of the ſick, and afterwards the ſweat is eaſily and ſoon rais'd; (whereas otherwiſe 'tis not only very difficultly procur'd in ſome bodies, but there is alſo danger leſt the inflammation ſhou'd be heigthen'd by it, and ſo the Tokens forc'd out) and the benefit of the ſweat immediately following, abundantly compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſates the loſs of blood, which how little ſoever it be wou'd otherwiſe be very injurious. After bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (which muſt be perform'd in bed, vvhen all things are in a readineſs to promote ſweat) vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any manner of delay, I order the Patient to be cover'd quite over vvith clothes, and that a piece of Flannel be bound to the forepart of his Head, and indeed this covering of the Head, conduces more to the procuring ſweat than any one vvou'd eaſily imagine. Afterwards if the Patient does not Vomit, I give theſe and the like Sudorifics.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take of Venice Treacle</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ii, <hi>of the Electuary of the Egg</hi> ℈i, <hi>of compound powder of Crabs eyes,</hi> gr. xii, <hi>of Cochinell</hi> gr. viii, <hi>of Saffron</hi> gr. iv, <hi>with a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient quantity of the juice of Kermes make a Bolus, which let him take every ſixth hour, drinking after it ſix spoonfuls of the following Julap.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take Cardus-water compound, Scordium-water of each</hi> ℥iii, <hi>Treacle-water</hi> ℥ii, <hi>Syrup of July-flowers</hi> ℥ii, <hi>mingle them and make a Julap.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But if the Patient be troubl'd vvith vomiting, as he is very frequently in the Plague, and other Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lential Fevers, I defer the giving of Sudorifics ſo
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:153471:16"/>
long as 'till he begins to ſweat, by means of the covering only, excepting that ſometimes I put part of the ſheet over the Face, to collect the vapors: for (which is indeed very well worth obſervation) when the rays of the Morbific matter extend themſelves to the circumference of the Body, the Looſneſs and Vomiting, that were occaſion'd by their being inwardly reflected and caſt upon the Stomac and Bowels, ceaſe preſently of their own accord. So that how great ſoever the preceding ſubverſion of the Stomac was, the Medicines that are taken afterwards are eaſily retain'd, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure ſweat as well as can be wiſh'd.</p>
                  <p>I remember, that being once call'd by an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecary to viſit his Brother, that was very ill of a Peſtilential Fever, and ſpeaking of giving him a Sudorific, he told me that he had taken various and ſtrong Medicines to procure Sweat, but all in vain, for that he had Vomited them all up; to whom I anſwer'd, that he ſhou'd prepare the moſt loathſom and ungrateful of all, that before he had exhibited; and that I wou'd eaſily effect, that he ſhou'd not Vomit it up any more. The event con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd what I promis'd, for when the Patient had Sweat a little, only by the weight of Clothes, he ſwallow'd and retain'd a large Bolus of <hi>Venice Treacle,</hi> by which means, Sweating plentifully, he recover'd.</p>
                  <p>But to return to the buſineſs, I order that the Sweat ſhou'd be continu'd, for the ſpace of a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral day, by <hi>Sage Poſſet-drink,</hi> or <hi>Mace-beer,</hi> now and then taken; and I ſtrictly forbid that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient ſhou'd be any way cleans'd; neither indeed do I permit that the Shirt, how moiſt or foul ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:153471:16"/>
it be, ſhou'd be chang'd, within the ſpace of Twenty four hours, from the end of the Sweat, which I wou'd have obſerv'd with the greateſt cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But if the Sweat be circumſcrib'd in a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower compaſs of time, the violence of the Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptoms ſoon returns, and the Health of the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent is left very uncertain, which a longer conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of the Sweat wou'd have put out of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
                  <p>And truly, I can't ſufficiently wonder at <hi>Die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merbroek</hi> and others, as often as I conſider upon how ſlight a pretence they are induc'd to break off the ſweat, to wit, that they may preſerve the ſtrength of the ſick. For, firſt, every one that is but very little converſant in the Cure of this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe knows that the Patient while he Sweats is ſtronger than he vvas before. What uſe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience have taught in this caſe, I vvill not fear to defend and declare openly. Many that have been Sweated, by my Advice, for the ſpace of Twenty four hours, have been ſo far from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of their being vveakn'd thereby, that they have profeſs'd that as much of the uſeleſs hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour was carried off by the Sweat, ſo much new ſtrength they receiv'd: and towards the latter end I have oft, not without admiration, obſerv'd a Sweat break out more natural, genuine and copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous than the former, which was expreſs'd by the force of the Medicine, and which brought much more relief, as if it were plainly and truly critical and eradicative of the whole Diſeaſe: moreover I don't perceive what inconvenience there wou'd be in refreſhing the Patient, when the Sweat is at height, with comfortable Soop and Broath; and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:153471:17"/>
then that Objection concerning want of ſtrength to bear long Sweats wou'd ſignifie nothing. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if any defection be perceiv'd, towards the latter end, I permit him to take a little Chicken Broath, the Yolk of an Egg or the like, which with Cordials and draughts commonly us'd, to keep up the Sweat, abundantly repair the ſtrength. But there's no need of many Arguments in a thing ſo obvious: for 'tis manifeſt, that as long as the Patient Sweats he thinks himſelf in a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and in the opinion of the ſtanders by the worſt is over, which openly proclaims the utility of this practice; but aſſoon as the Sweat is ſtopt, and the Body begins to dry, he falls ill again, and there is as it were a relapſe.</p>
                  <p>I admoniſh that cold be carefully avoided, that the Clothes dry on the Body of their own accord, and that all Drinks are taken ſomewhat hot, and that the uſe of Sage Poſſet-drink be continued for the ſpace of Twenty four hours after the Sweat. The next morning I give a common Purge, to wit, <hi>of the Infuſion of Tamarinds, of the Leaves of Senna, of Rhubarb, with Manna, and Syrrup of Roſes ſolutive.</hi> And with this method, the next year af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Plague, I recover'd very many that were feiz'd with the Peſtilential Fever; ſo that not one died of this Diſeaſe, that was under my Care, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I began the uſe of the ſame.</p>
                  <p>But where the tumour has been out already, I have not hitherto dar'd to bleed, tho' in a Body <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>apt to Sweat, fearing leſt the ſudden Death of the Patient ſhou'd prevent the deſign'd Sweat, by reaſon of the Morbific matter flowing back to the empty Veins; yet perhaps Phlebotomy may be
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:153471:17"/>
very ſafely adminiſtred, if Sweat be procur'd pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after it, without any manner of delay, which being prolong'd to the ſpace above requir'd, may be able to diſſipate and conſume by little and little the whole bulk of the humour, and with much leſs danger, than when a legitimate maturation of the Impoſthume, (which is very uncertain and fallible in ſo very acute a Diſeaſe) is long waited for.</p>
                  <p>To conclude, if the Reader ſhall find that I have been any where miſtaken about the Theory, I beg pardon; but as to practice, I declare that I have faithfully deliver'd all things, and that I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver propos'd any thing before I had ſufficiently try'd it. Truly when I come to dye, I truſt, I ſhall have a chearful witneſs in my Breaſt, that I have not only with the greateſt diligence and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty endeavour'd the recovery of the health of all, of what condition ſoever they have been, that have committed themſelves to my care (of whom none was otherwiſe treated by me, than I deſire to be manag'd if I ſhould happen to have the ſame Diſeaſes) but that alſo I have labour'd to the utmoſt of my power, that the Cure of Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes (if by any means it might be) may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter'd with greater certainty after I am Dead, Eſteeming any progreſs in this kind of Knowledg, how ſmall ſo ever it be, tho' it teach no more than the Cure of the <hi>Tooth-ach,</hi> or of <hi>Corns,</hi> to be more valued than the vain pomp of nice Specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which perhaps are no more uſeful to a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian, in the Cure of Diſeaſes, than Skill in Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick to a Carpenter in <hi>Building.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:153471:18"/>
In the laſt place, I will add only this one ſhort Note, leſt perchance any one ſhou'd wreſt my O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion by a ſiniſter Interpretation, or at leaſt not throughly underſtand it; to wit, that in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding Diſcourſe, I often uſe the word Nature, and attribute various effects to her, as if I would repreſent under this Title, ſome one thing ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of it ſelf, and diffus'd every where through the whole Machin of the World, which being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow'd with Reaſon, governs all Bodies: ſuch a thing as ſome of the Philoſophers ſeem'd to think was the Soul of the World. But as I don't af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect novelty of things, ſo neither of words: and therefore I uſe in theſe Pages, the Ancient word indeed, but in a ſenſe (unleſs I am deceiv'd) both ſober, and not only underſtood, but alſo us'd by the beſt Men. For as often as I mention Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, I wou'd ſignifie a certain <hi>complex of Natural Cauſes,</hi> which tho' they are without Reaſon, and deſtitute of all Skill, yet are they govern'd by the beſt Counſel; whil'ſt all of them perform their Operations, and accompliſh their effects. To wit, the ſupream Deity, by whoſe Power all things are produc'd, and on whoſe pleaſure they depend, has ſo diſpos'd all things by his infinite Wiſdom, that they betake themſelves to their appointed Functions in a certain order and method, doing nothing that's in vain, but that which is beſt and fitteſt for the whole Fabric of things, and their own private Natures; and ſo are mov'd, like <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines,</hi> not by their own Skill but by that of the Artificer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:153471:18"/>
               <head>COLLECTIONS OF <hi>Acute Diſeaſes.</hi>
               </head>
               <head>The Third Part:</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. I. Of the continual Fever of the Year 1661. 1662. 63. 64.</head>
                  <p>FIRST, I obſerve that the inordinate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion of the Blood the Cauſe or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion of this Fever, is ſtirr'd up by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, either that ſome Heterogenious matter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd in it and inimical to it ſhou'd be excluded, or that the Blood ſhou'd be chang'd into ſome new diſpoſition.</p>
                  <p>And in this buſineſs the word <hi>Commotion</hi> pleaſes me beſt, becauſe 'tis more large and general than
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:153471:19"/>
either <hi>Fermentation</hi> or <hi>Ebullition,</hi> for it prevents the occaſion of a vain Diſpute about Terms, that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps words of that kind may ſeem to countenance; tho' they may admit of an Explication that is not incommodious, yet are thought a little improper and harſh by ſome: for tho' the <hi>Commotion</hi> of the Blood may be ſometimes like the <hi>Fermentation,</hi> ſometimes like the <hi>Ebullition</hi> of Vegetable Liquors, yet there are ſome that think it very much differs from both, and they produce one or two inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Fermentation. Firſt, tho' Liquids fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting are wont to obtain a vinous nature, ſo that Diſtillation will draw a hot Spirit from them, and eaſily degenerate into Vineger, which is indow'd with a notable ſowerneſs, and by Diſtillation yeilds an Acid Spirit; yet they ſay that neither of theſe diſpoſitions has hitherto been obſerved in the Blood.</p>
                  <p>And they take notice that in vinous Liquors the <hi>Fermentation</hi> and <hi>Depuration</hi> are finiſh'd at the ſame time, and as it were keep pace together; but the Depuration of the Blood in Fevers does not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company but follows its <hi>Aeſtuation,</hi> which they think is manifeſt even to ſight, in a Febrile Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roxyſm carried off by Sweat.</p>
                  <p>But as to <hi>Ebullition,</hi> the Analogy ſeems more difficult to them, and which experience diſallows in many caſes, where the fury of the Blood is not ſo outragious as that it may deſerve the name of Ebullition: but however it be (for I will by no means ingage in theſe Controverſies) ſeeing the terms of <hi>Ebullition</hi> and <hi>Fermentation</hi> have very much prevail'd among Modern Phyſitians, I ſhall not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to uſe them now and then, whil'ſt 'tis mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:153471:19"/>
from what has been ſaid, that theſe words ſerve only in this Treatiſe for the more clear explication of what is to be diſcours'd of.</p>
                  <p>Certainly all kind of Fevers that are accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Eruptions, manifeſt that this Febrile com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion of the Blood, is ſtirr'd up for the Secreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a certain Heterogeneous matter that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to nature: for that in theſe, by the help of Ebullition, an Excrement of an ill quality is caſt forth to the skin that lay hid before in the Blood.</p>
                  <p>And 'tis not leſs probable in my Opinion, that the Febrile commotion of the Blood, ſhou'd often (not to ſay oftner) aim at no more than to be chang'd into a certain new ſtate and diſpoſition, and that a Man whoſe Blood continues pure and untainted may be ſeiz'd with a Fever, as by fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent obſervations we find it happens to healthy Bodies, in whom there is no Morbific furniture, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as to a <hi>Plethora</hi> or ill habit, no unhealthy diſpoſition of the Air, which may adminiſter oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion for a Fever, and yet notwithſtanding by reaſon of ſome notable alteration of the Air pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding, or change of Diet, or of the reſt of the Non-naturals as they are term'd, ſuch Men are likewiſe ſeiz'd with a Fever; and the reaſon is, becauſe the Blood endeavours to gain a new ſtate or condition, ſuch as the Air and manner of Diet require; not that the irritation of vicious Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles lodg'd in the Blood, cauſe the Fever, tho' I don't at all doubt but that the matter that is ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily Excreted in the Deſpumation of the Blood, after the Febrile Commotion, is vicious, tho' the Blood before had a laudable Diatheſis, which is
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:153471:20"/>
no more to be wonder'd at than that ſome part of what we Eat ſhou'd turn to Corruption, and ſtink after it has been conſiderably alter'd in the Body and ſeperated from the reſt.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, I reckon that the true and natural in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dications that ariſe in this Diſeaſe, ſhew that the Commotion of the Blood muſt be kept to that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree which is agreeable to Natures purpoſe, that it don't riſe too high on the one Hand, from whence great Symptoms flow, nor be depreſs'd too low on the other; by which means the Protruſion of the Morbific matter may be hinder'd, or the endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of the Blood Affecting a new condition, fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated; ſo that whether the Fever takes its riſe from ſome Heterogeneous matter provoking it, or from the Blood affecting a new ſtate; in either caſe the Indication is the ſame: theſe things being premis'd, I inſtitute the method of Cure after this manner.</p>
                  <p>When I am call'd to Patients whoſe Blood of it ſelf is weak (as 'tis moſt times in Children) or when it wants Spirits, as in old Age, and in young Men weaken'd by long Diſeaſes, I forbear Phle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>botomy; for if I ſhou'd bleed ſuch, their Blood being already too weak, it wou'd be render'd al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together unfit to perform the buſineſs of Deſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and by conſequence the whole maſs wou'd be perverted, and perchance the Life of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient hazarded (as when the Fermentation of Beer or any new Liquor is unſeaſonably ſtopt, 'tis moſt commonly ſpoil'd) for Nature can no more aſſociate with the Particles it has once begun to Exterminate, which tho' they were pure, whil'ſt they were equally mixt with the maſs of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:153471:20"/>
Blood, yet now they are corrupt and apt to infect the other Humours. Indeed I know very well that thoſe that are injured by bleeding are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times reſtor'd by proper Cordials, ſo that the Blood is inabled to purifie it ſelf, but 'tis better to prevent than Cure a Diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>But when I have to do with thoſe whoſe Blood is of a contrary Nature, ſuch as is wont to be in young Men, of a Robuſt conſtitution and Sanguine complexion; I order bleeding in the firſt place, which can't be omitted here without hazard (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide in ſome caſes to be mention'd hereafter) for otherwiſe not only Phrenſies, Pleuriſies, and ſuch like Inflammations may be fear'd, upon the account of too great Ebullition of the Blood, but alſo by reaſon of the ſuperfluity, a Stagnation of the whole maſs.</p>
                  <p>As to the quantity, I only take away ſo much Blood as I conceive will free the ſick from thoſe dangers, to which as we ſaid, the immoderate Commotion of the ſame is obnoxious. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, I regulate the Eſtuation by repeating Phle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>botomy, or omitting it, by uſing or forbidding the uſe of hot Cordials; and laſtly, by keeping the Body looſe, or ſtoping it as I perceive that motion is high or low.</p>
                  <p>After bleeding (if it be neceſſary according to the caſes above mention'd) I diligently inquire whether the Patient was inclin'd to vomiting, or nauſeouſneſs, at the beginning of the Fever, and if ſo, I preſently preſcribe a Vomit, unleſs the tender Age or ſome great Debility of the Sick forbid it. Truly a Vomit is ſo neceſſary, when an inclination to Vomiting has preceded, that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:153471:21"/>
unleſs that Humour be expell'd, it will occaſion many difficult Symptoms, that will hinder the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian in performing the Cure, and will very much endanger the Patient; a <hi>Diarrhaea</hi> is the chief and moſt uſual of theſe, which moſt commonly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows in the declination of the Fever, as often as <hi>Emetics</hi> are indicated and yet omitted; for in the progreſs of the Fever, when Nature has ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſubjugated the malign Humour in the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, and thruſt it forth to the Guts, they are ſo corroded by a perpetual Flux of a ſharp Humour, from this fountain in the Stomach, that a <hi>Diarrhaea</hi> muſt needs follow. But I have obſerv'd that in Inflammatory Fevers, that are commonly call'd Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant, a <hi>looſneſs</hi> did not neceſſarily follow the omiſſion of a Vomit, as in this Fever, tho' ſuch a propenſity to Vomiting preceded.</p>
                  <p>This kind of <hi>Diarrhaea</hi> is more dangerous, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Sick being ſufficiently weakn'd before is more Enervated; beſides (which is worſt) it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens at the declination of the Fever, at which time the Blood ſhou'd contract it ſelf, and exert its faculty, for the compleating its Deſpumation, but is hinder'd by this evacuation.</p>
                  <p>But that you may not doubt that this Humour lodg'd in the Stomach, unleſs it be ejected by Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, will in a ſhort time cauſe a <hi>Diarrhaea;</hi> by ſearch we almoſt always find, that when a <hi>looſneſs</hi> accompanies this Fever, the Sick was inclin'd to Vomit at the beginning of the Diſeaſe, but a <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit</hi> was not preſcrib'd. Moreover you will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that tho' the inclination to vomiting went off long ago, yet the <hi>Diarrhaea</hi> will ceaſe for the moſt part upon taking a Vomit, if the Patient be
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:153471:21"/>
able to bear it; but I have often obſerv'd, that when the <hi>Diarrhaea</hi> is once begun, Aſtringent Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines ſignifie little or nothing, either inwardly taken or outwardly apply'd to ſtop it.</p>
                  <p>The Vomit I frequently uſe is this following,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take of the Infuſion of Crocus Metall.</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>vi, <hi>Oxy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel of Squills and compound Syrup of Scabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of each</hi> ℥ſſ. <hi>Mingle them and make a Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which I order to be taken in the Afternoon, two Hours after a light Dinner; and that the Vomit may ſucceed the better, I appoint ſix or eight pints of <hi>Poſſet-drink</hi> to be provided, for theſe Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines are dangerous, if they are not waſh'd off; and therefore as often as the Patient Vomits or goes to Stool, he muſt preſently take a draught of it, by which means the Gripes will be prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and he will Vomit eaſier.</p>
                  <p>After a nice view of the matter ejected by Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, which was neither much nor very ill, I have often wonder'd how it comes to paſs, that the ſick ſhou'd be ſo much reliv'd by it; for aſſoon as the Vomit had done Working, the cruel Symptoms, to wit, the Nauſeouſneſs, Anxiety, Reſtleſsneſs, Sighings and Blackneſs of the Tongue, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were commonly mitigated, which before tormented the Sick, and terrified the ſtanders by, ſo that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of the Diſeaſe was very tolerable.</p>
                  <p>Tis to be noted, that if the condition of the Patient require Bleeding and Vomiting, 'tis ſafeſt to bleed firſt, for otherwiſe whil'ſt the Veſſels are diſtended with Blood, there is great danger leſt
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:153471:22"/>
by violent ſtraining to Vomit, the Veſſels of the Lungs ſhou'd be broken, and the Brain hurt, the Blood being impetuouſly pour'd in and out, and ſo the Patient may dye Apoplectic, of which I could produce ſome Examples if I thought it convenient; let it ſuffice that I warn you to uſe great caution in this caſe.</p>
                  <p>If any one ſhou'd ask at what time of the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver I would give a Vomit? I ſay at the very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, If I had my choice, for by this means the Sick may be defended from thoſe horrid Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptoms that take their riſe from the filth of thoſe Humours that lurk in the Stomach and neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing parts, and perhaps we may cruſh the Diſeaſe in its beginning, which othewiſe wou'd increaſe to the hazard of the Patient; and prove tedious, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nouriſh'd by the foreſaid Humours, which ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by reaſon of their ſubſtance paſs into the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nermoſt parts of the Body, and are mingl'd with the Blood, or becauſe they are too long detain'd in the Body they wax worſe, and put on a vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous quality which they impart to the Blood, as it continually paſſes by their Neaſt; and of this (not to go far) the <hi>Cholera Morbus</hi> is a clear ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, for it happens ſometimes, that when the Vomiting is unſeaſonably ſtopt in that Diſeaſe, whether it be by an Opiat, or Aſtringent Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, a worſe train of Symptoms follow; for the ſharp and corrupted Humours being repell'd upon this account, whoſe excluſion ought to have been permitted a while till they were ſufficiently eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuated, exert their fury and force upon the Blood, and kindle a Fever; which as tis wont to be ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regular and accompanied with ill Symptoms, ſo it
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:153471:22"/>
can ſcarce be Cur'd without an <hi>Emetic,</hi> tho' the Patient do not then Vomit.</p>
                  <p>But if we are call'd in late, (as we are often) ſo that we can't aſſiſt the Patient at the beginning of the Fever by preſcribing a Vomit, yet I have thought it proper to order one at any time of the Diſeaſe, provided the Patient hath ſtrength enough to bear the operation of it. Truly I have given an <hi>Emetic</hi> with good ſucceſs, on the 12th day of the Fever, tho' the Patient had left off Vomiting before; and ſo I have ſtopt the <hi>looſneſs</hi> which hinder'd the Blood in finiſhing its Deſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; and I ſhou'd not doubt to preſcribe one later unleſs the weakneſs of the Patient for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid it.</p>
                  <p>The Evening after taking the Vomit, I always endeavour to quiet the tumult rais'd in the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours by the <hi>Emetic,</hi> and therefore I preſcribe an Anodyne to be taken at Bed-time. For inſtance,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take of Erratic Poppy-water</hi> ℥ii, <hi>of Aq. Mirab.</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ii, <hi>Syrup of white and Erratic Poppies of each</hi> ℥ſſ. <hi>Mingle them and make a draught.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But if there be no fear of raiſing the Ebullition for the future, either by reaſon of a great loſs of Blood which was taken away in order to the Cure, or by frequent <hi>Vomiting</hi> and <hi>Stools</hi> occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd by the <hi>Emetic,</hi> or by a preſent <hi>Apurexy,</hi> or Debility of the Fever, or its declining ſtate; then I boldly order a large doſe of <hi>Diaſcordium,</hi> either by it ſelf, or mixt with ſome Cordial Water in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of the Anodyne preſcrib'd above, and 'tis indeed an excellent Medicine if it be given in a due quantity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:153471:23"/>
And now before I leave off diſcourſing of <hi>Eme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tics,</hi> I muſt acquaint you that 'tis by no means ſafe (at leaſt in this Fever) to give Vomits of the infuſion of <hi>Crocus Metallorum</hi> to Children, or to any under fourteen, no not in the leaſt quantity; 'twere to be wiſh'd, that in the room of this we had ſome ſafer Medicine that were as efficacious, which may eradicate the Humour, that almoſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways threatens a <hi>Diarrhaea,</hi> at the Declination of the Fever, at leaſt that we had ſuch a one as wou'd ſo change the corroſive matter, that it cou'd not cauſe a <hi>looſneſs;</hi> truly I have been often puzzel'd, when I have been call'd to Infants or Children in a Fever, and have beheld an indication which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded the uſe of a Medicine that wou'd have Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them, and yet I did not dare to preſcribe it for fear of the ill conſequence; but in grown peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple I have hitherto obſerv'd no injury to proceed from the uſe of an <hi>Emetic,</hi> provided it be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter'd with the cautions above mention'd.</p>
                  <p>The fatigue of Vomiting being over, I further conſider with my ſelf, whether notwithſtanding the preceding Evacuations, the Blood continues yet to rage ſo much, that 'tis ſtill neceſſary to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain its Efferveſcence, or whether it be ſo very Languid that it wants to be heigthen'd; or laſtly, whether the Fermentation being reduc'd to a due degree, may be left to it ſelf without danger to the Patient: Of each of theſe I ſhall ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Therefore if the Blood Ferments ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently that we may yet reaſonably ſuſpect that the Patient is either obnoxious to a Phrenſie, or any other troubleſom Symptom proceeding from
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:153471:23"/>
too great an Ebullition of the Blood; the day after taking the Vomit, I preſcribe a Clyſter. For inſtance,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take of the common Decoction for a Clyſter</hi> 
                     <abbr>lb</abbr>i, <hi>Syrup of Violets and brown Suggar, of each</hi> ℥ii. <hi>Mingle them and make a Clyſter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And I order it ſhou'd be repeated upon occaſion, by which it often happens that the Blood being ſomewhat Ventilated and Cool, its Efferveſcence is ſufficiently bridl'd, but ſometimes 'tis neceſſary to repeat bleeding once and again, <hi>viz.</hi> in thoſe of a very Sanguine complexion, and in the flower of their Age, or in others who have imprinted on their Blood a certain inflammatory diſpoſition, by too frequent uſe of Wine. But for the moſt part there is no need of ſo great a Remedy (as is repeated Phlebotomy) and excepting the caſes above men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd, that Efferveſcence may be ſufficiently ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd by the help of <hi>Clyſters;</hi> wherefore if the Blood Ferment too much, I order a <hi>Clyſter</hi> to be injected every day, or every other day, as the caſe requires, and that it be done to the tenth day of the Diſeaſe or thereabouts; but if much Blood has been take away, or the Patient is Ag'd, I order no <hi>Clyſters</hi> at that time, tho' the Blood be very hot; for in theſe caſes as there is no fear that by the omiſſion of <hi>Clyſters</hi> the Ebullition be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun ſhou'd proceed ſo far as that there ſhou'd be eminent danger from ſome violent Symptom: So its moſt certain that by the uſe of them the ſtrength, and as I may ſay, tho' leſs properly, the Tone of the Blood is ſo much indeed relax'd, that eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:153471:24"/>
in old Men, (for <hi>Clyſters</hi> are not uſed with ſo good ſucceſs in old Men as in young) Nature is obſtructed in her buſineſs; but if a Vein has been open'd, and not much Blood taken away, then as I ſaid, I order <hi>Clyſters</hi> to the tenth day more or leſs, and ſometimes to the twelfth, eſpecially for thoſe I did not dare bleed; for there are ſome that are ſeiz'd with continual Fevers, after Autumnal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termittents (whether they were Tertian or Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan) by reaſon they were not purg'd after theſe Agues left them; and if you ſhou'd Bleed them there wou'd be danger leſt that Sediment, which the foregoing Fermentation put off, ſhou'd be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorb'd into the maſs of Blood, and ſo ſhou'd oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion new Tumults; therefore in this caſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Bleeding I uſe <hi>Clyſters</hi> to the twelfth day, if the Patient be young and the Fermentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on too high.</p>
                  <p>But on the contrary, whether Bleeding be us'd or omitted if the Efferveſcence be too Languid, and wants to be ſtirr'd up to aſſiſt Nature; in this caſe I ſuppoſe we muſt wholly abſtain from the uſe of <hi>Clyſters,</hi> even before the tenth day, and much rather if it be paſt: for to what purpoſe ſhou'd we endeavour any further to ſuppreſs the Fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation which is too Languid already? but if after that time, to wit, in the declination of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe we ſhou'd uſe <hi>Clyſters,</hi> it wou'd indeed be as abſurd, as if any one ſhou'd give too large vent to Beer when 'tis dying, for by means of this Evacuation Nature is hinder'd, ſo that ſhe can't at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the ſeparation of the Morbific matter with all her might; when therefore by means of fit Evacuations the Patient is out of danger as to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:153471:24"/>
thoſe Symptoms which proceed from too great Ebullition, or the Diſeaſe is in its declination; the more I bind his Body, the farther he is out of danger, to wit the Febrile matter tending gently to its own Concoction. Wherefore if the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Evacuations have induc'd as it were a Laxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the maſs of Blood, or threaten the ſame, or if the Patient be freed from his Fever before the due time; or if the Fever has come to a full period, I do not only leave off the uſe of <hi>Clyſters,</hi> but think that Cordials are to be allow'd, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently endeavour to ſtop the Belly.</p>
                  <p>But as to <hi>Cordials,</hi> for I have found by Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that the too early uſe of them has been very injurious, to wit (Bleeding having not been firſt us'd) there is danger leſt the crude matter ſhou'd fall upon the Membranes of the Brain or the like, or on the Pleura; and therefore I always take care that Cordials be not given, when no Blood or but very little has been taken away, and there has been no other conſiderable Evacuation, or when the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient has not paſs'd the vigour of his Age: for I can't ſee to what purpoſe his Blood that is rich enough of it ſelf, ſhou'd be further Meliorated to his own ruine; but rich and opulent enough it is, neither wants it Reſtoratives, as long as conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Evacuations have not vanquiſh'd its innate heat. Such Patients are ſufficiently furniſh'd with Cordials within themſelves, and as to thoſe which come from abroad, they are either needleſs or elſe are hurtful; wherefore I wou'd either wholly reject all, or at leaſt admit of only the ſmalleſt. But if the Patient be weaken'd by profuſe Evacuations, or be Ag'd, I uſe to give Cordials even at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:153471:25"/>
of the Fever, but on the twelfth day of the Diſeaſe, things then tending to Secretion, I ſuppoſe we ought freely to indulge the uſe of hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Medicines, and indeed a little ſooner, if there be no danger of driving the Febrile matter upon the principal parts. For at this time the more I heat, ſo much the more I accelerate Concoction; neither truly can I imagine what Phyſitians wou'd be at, who ſo often inculcate their Precepts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the adminiſtring of Remedies to promote the Concoction of the Febrile matter, which they often do, being call'd in at the beginning of the Diſeaſe; and yet at the ſame time notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they don't doubt to preſcribe ſuch kind of Medicines as attemperate the Fever; for indeed a Fever is Natures Inſtrument, by which ſhe ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates the impure parts from the pure: by this means utterly Imperceptible, ſhe proceeds from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the highth of the Diſeaſe, but performs the buſineſs more manifeſtly at its declination, which may be diſcern'd by the Urine. The <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction</hi> of the Febrile matter denotes no more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed than the ſeparation of the peccant matter from the good; now in the haſtenning of it you muſt not buſie your ſelf with I know not what at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperaters, but the Efferveſcence of the Fever is to be let alone, ſo long as the ſafety of the Patient will permit; but when it tends to the declination, Secretion being manifeſt, then we ſhou'd follow it with hotter Medicines to finiſh the buſineſs ſooner and ſafer; and this is indeed to promote the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction of the Febrile matter: whereas Evacuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Coolers cauſe delays and hinder the Cure, and drive away approaching Health, as I have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten obſerved.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:153471:25"/>
If the Fermentation proceed well, the <hi>Deſpuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> will be finiſhed about the fourteenth day, but if you uſe any Coolers too late, and ſo by their means ſuppreſs the Efferveſcence, 'tis not ſtrange if the Fever continue till the twenty firſt day, and in fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Bodies ill manag'd much longer.</p>
                  <p>Moreover this is worth Obſervation; that it ſometimes happens that the Patient by the uſe of <hi>Clyſters</hi> and other Catharticks unſeaſonably pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd, about the declination of the Diſeaſe, ſeems a little reliev'd, and ſometimes is wholly freed from his Fever; but after a day or two you will perceive not ſo much that the old Fever has recover'd ſtrength as that a new one is broke out, <hi>viz.</hi> a ſhaking and horror preſently invade, which heat and a Fever preſently ſucceed, about to run the ſame courſe which was deſcrib'd above, unleſs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance it change to an Intermittent. When the caſe is ſo, the Patient is to be treated as if he had no Fever before, and the ſame method is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, for <hi>Deſpumation,</hi> which ſhou'd follow the <hi>Ebullition</hi> now begun, will not be finiſh'd in leſs than the time before mention'd, how tedious ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it wou'd be to the Patient, much weakn'd by the former Diſeaſe, to wait ſo long for health.</p>
                  <p>The Cordials I preſcribe are ſuch as theſe, which I will mention by and by; thoſe that are more moderate I uſe at the beginning of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, when the heat is very violent, always pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding gradually to the uſe of hotter, according to the progreſs of the Diſeaſe and the degrees of <hi>Ebullition;</hi> always remembring that its lawful, if much Blood has been taken away, or if the Patient be Ag'd, to adminiſter ſtronger Cordials than when
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:153471:26"/>
Bleeding has not preceded, or when the Patient was in the flower of his Age.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe Cordials, I call moderate, are made of diſtilled Waters, for inſtance, of Borage, Citron, Strawberries, Treacle, compound Scordium water, mingled with the Syrup of Baulm, of Fernelius, of Julyflowers, of the juice of Citron, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but the ſtronger of Gaſcoins Powder, Bezoar, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of Hyacinth, Venice Treacle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe which follow are frequently us'd.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take of the water of Borage, Citron, compound Scordium water, Black Cherries, each</hi> ℥ii, <hi>Cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon water with Barly</hi> ℥i, <hi>Pearls prepar'd</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ii, <hi>Cryſtalline Sugar a ſufficient quantity, mingle them. Take four ſpoonfuls often in a day eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the Fits.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take of the water of the whole Citron, of Straw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berries each</hi> ℥iii, <hi>of the cold Cordial water of Saxony</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>i, <hi>of Treacle water, of Syrup of Baulm, of Fernelius, of Julyflowers, and of the juice of Citron, each</hi> ℥ſſ, <hi>mingle them and make a Julap, of which take often.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take of Gaſcoins powder, of the Oriental and Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidental Bezoar-ſtone, of Contrayerva, each</hi> ℈i, <hi>one leaf of Gold, mingle them and make a very fine Powder. Take to the quantity of twelve grains when there is occaſion, in the Syrup of the juice of Citron and Julyflowers, each</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ii, <hi>drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon it a few ſpoonfuls of the Julap pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:153471:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <hi>Take of Treacle water</hi> ℥iv, <hi>of the Seeds of Citron</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ii, <hi>beat them together and make an Emulſion: Add to the ſtrain'd liquor a ſufficient quantity of Pearl Sugar to make it grateful to the Taſte. Take two ſpoonfuls three times a day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I think 'tis needleſs to mention more forms, for they are innumerable or may be ſo, and they are to be varied in the courſe of the Diſeaſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the various Seaſons and Symptoms.</p>
                  <p>But if the Fermentation be neither too high nor too low, I leave it in that ſtate and uſe no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, unleſs I am forc'd to do ſomething by the importunity of the Sick or his Friends about him, that may pleaſe them, without obſtructing my deſign.</p>
                  <p>And now I muſt tell you, that when I was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to a poor Body who was not able to be at the charge of going through a long courſe of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, I did nothing elſe after Bleeding and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging was over, (if they were indicated) but or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them to keep their Beds, all the time of their Sickneſs, and to drink Oatmeal, and Barley Broath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that they ſhould drink ſmall Bear warm, moderately to quench their thirſt. I took care that they ſhou'd have a <hi>Clyſter</hi> of Milk and Sugar every day or every other day, till the tenth or eleventh day, and towards the end of the Fever, ſeparation being now begun, if it were ſlow, I permitted them now and then ſtronger drink to help it inſtead of a Cordial, and ſo without any more a do, except that I uſe to give a gentle Purge at the end of the Diſeaſe, I cur'd them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:153471:27"/>
But to return to the buſineſs, if the method be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mention'd be carefully obſerv'd, I uſually per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive about the fifteenth day, both from the Signs of a laudable ſeparation in the Urine, as alſo from a manifeſt remiſſion of all the Symptoms, that 'tis then ſeaſonable to give a purging Poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which may carry off the Sediment, put off here and there by the foregoing Fermentation; and unleſs it is done timely there is danger leſt it ſhou'd return into the maſs of Blood, and ſo cauſe a relapſe, or by its abode in the Natural parts upon which 'tis thrown, occaſion hereafter a dreadful Minera of laſting ills in the Body, <hi>viz.</hi> Seperation being now finiſh'd the groſs and impure Humours ſent from the Arteries to the Blood, paſſing back into the Veins, eaſily hinder its re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, from whence various kinds of Obſtructions and at length various Fermentations do ariſe.</p>
                  <p>But 'tis to be obſerv'd that Purging is not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſo neceſſary, after Vernal Fevers as after Autumnal; and for this reaſon, becauſe the Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment put off by Autumnals is more, and of a more Terrene and Malignant quality, and which is alſo to be noted in the Small Pox, and many other Diſeaſes raging in the Spring, in which 'tis not ſo dangerous to omit Purging (which indeed I have obſerv'd) as in the caſe before menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd.</p>
                  <p>And truly he wou'd not be much miſtaken who ſhou'd affirm that more Diſeaſes take their riſe from hence, (to wit, from the omiſſion of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging after Autumnal Diſeaſes) than from any other cauſe whatever.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:153471:27"/>
If the Patient be very weak, or if there be not a perfect Deſpumation, ſo that I can't boldly give a Purge on the fifteenth day, I defer it to the ſeventeenth, at which time I give the following or the like, according to the ſtrength of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take of Tamarinds ℥ſſ, of the Leaves of Sennna</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ii, <hi>Rubarb</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>iſſ, <hi>boyl them in a ſufficient quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of water, to three ounces of the ſtrained Liquor; add Syrup of Roſes, Solutive and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, of each one ounce; mingle them and make a potion to be taken in the Morning.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Purging being over, I order the Patient to riſe, who has been hitherto kept abed by my preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, and to return gradually to his accuſtom'd diet; for that which I have hitherto preſcrib'd is in a manner the ſame with that which I have men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd before, as Oaten and Barly broaths, and Panado made of Bread, and the Yolk of an Egg in water with Sugar, thin Chicken broath, ſmall Beer; and ſometimes when the Fever is high the juice of Orange newly expreſs'd, and a little boyld to take off the Crudity mixt with it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> tho' Oatmeal broath is as good as any; but to deny ſmall Bear to be taken now and then moderately, is a needleſs ſeverity, and indeed very often hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
                  <p>It happens often (eſpecially in old Men) that the Patient, tho' the Fever be Cur'd and the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſufficiently purg'd, is notwithſtanding very weak, and ſometimes expectorates by Cough, and ſometimes alſo hauks up a great quantity of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:153471:28"/>
clammy Phlegm, which Symptom does not only afrighten the Patient, but alſo impoſes upon the Phyſitian, eſpecially if he be unwary, and induces him to believe that this effect will make way for a Conſumption, tho' I have obſerv'd that the thing is not ſo very dangerous. In this caſe I order the Patient to drink old Malago, or Muſcadine with a Toaſt, which (corroborating the Craſis of the Blood, much weakned by the foregoing Fever, and by conſequence unable to aſſimulate the juices of the meat lately eaten) takes off that Symptom in the ſpace of few days, as I have often experienc'd.</p>
                  <p>By this method which I have propos'd, the ſick will be ſecur'd from many affects and Symptoms which are wont to be attributed to Malignity; for nothing is more common with unskilful Phyſitians than to put the fault upon <hi>malignity:</hi> When by cooling Medicines, and the unſeaſonable uſe of Clyſters, they have ſo relax'd the Craſis of the Blood, and ſo weakn'd Nature in performing the Deſpumation of it, that Faintings and other Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptoms (which are indeed genuine effects of ſuch impediments occaſion'd by Art) happen. But if the Diſeaſe by its long continuance free it ſelf from this aſperſion, then what ever afterwards obſtructs the Cure, is attributed to the <hi>Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy;</hi> tho' in truth neither the Symptoms which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd while the Diſeaſe was in its vigor, were the effects of <hi>Malignity,</hi> nor thoſe which happen in its declination of the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> but both proceed from ill management, as I have often obſerv'd. Not that I or any other perſon who has been but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle converſant in the Hiſtory of Diſeaſes can be ignorant, that there are Fevers which don't only
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:153471:28"/>
conſiſt of an Intemperies or putrid heat, but alſo of a <hi>malignant</hi> quality, whoſe moſt evident Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptoms cannot but appear in the Sick; or that I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that ſometimes the <hi>Scurvy,</hi> and very many other Diſeaſes may be complicated with a Fever, I ſay only that theſe affections are many times unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly blam'd.</p>
                  <p>If the Fermentation proceed well, there will be a perfect Deſpumation of the Morbific matter within the time aforeſaid; but if cooling Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies or Clyſters have been given too late, the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver will continue much longer, eſpecially in very ancient Men ill manag'd by the Phyſitian. I have been ſometimes call'd to ſuch, after they have la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour'd under a Fever forty days or more, and have try'd all things to induce Deſpumation to the Blood, but it was ſo much weaken'd, partly by old Age, and partly by Clyſters and cooling Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, that I cou'd not attain my end either by Cordials or any other Corroborating Medicines; but either their Fever ſtood its ground, or if otherwiſe it ſeem'd to ceaſe, the Patients ſtrength was very low and in a manner gone.</p>
                  <p>But other Remedies being unſucceſsfully us'd, I have been often forc'd to take this courſe, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed with very good ſucceſs, <hi>viz.</hi> I have apply'd the brisk heat of young People to the Sick. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there any reaſon why any one ſhou'd much wonder that the Patient is ſo mightily ſtrengthen'd, and weak Nature reliev'd by this method, tho' it be unuſual, as that it can deliver it ſelf from the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of the matter to be Eliminated, ſeeing 'tis eaſie to conceive a Transfuſion of a great quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of vigorous Effluvias, from the ſound and ſtrong
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:153471:29"/>
Body, into the wither'd one of the Sick, neither have I ever found that the repeated application of hot clothes cou'd at all do that which the now mention'd method has perform'd, where both the heat apply'd is more agreeable to the humane Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and gentle, moiſt, equal and laſting; and tho' this way of immitting Balſamic Spirits into the Body of the Patient might ſeem abſurd at the time when I preſcrib'd it, yet it has been us'd by others with happy ſucceſs; neither truly am I aſham'd to mention this remedy, tho' perhaps ſome impertinent Men ſuperciliouſly contemning all things Vulgar may ridicule me for it. For I think the Health and Good of my Neighbour is very much to be preferr'd before their vain Opinions.</p>
                  <p>He that prudently and with due conſideration hath obſerv'd the method hitherto deliver'd, will free the Patient, if not from all, yet at leaſt from moſt of thoſe Symptoms which are either wont to accompany the Fever or to come after it, and which render the Phyſitian doubtful and at a loſs in the courſe of the Cure, and often deſtroy his Patient, tho' the nature of the Diſeaſe does not ſeem deadly. But for as much as ſuch accidents often happen, either becauſe the Sick neglected to call the Phyſitian in time, or by reaſon of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfulneſs or careleſſneſs of the Phyſitian. I think it not amiſs to treat briefly of their pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Cure, but will only confine my ſelf to thoſe Symptoms, which tho' they might often have been prevented, if the foreſaid method had been us'd, yet when they happen they require a different Cure proper to themſelves.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:153471:29"/>
And to begin from hence, if the Sick <note place="margin">A Phrenſie.</note> either upon the account of taking hot Medicines unſeaſonably, or by being naturally of too hot a conſtitution fall into a Phrenſie, or (which is next to it) if he does not ſleep at all, often calls out or uſes incoherent Speeches; if he looks and talks fierce, if he takes Medicines and common Drink greedily and as it were ſnatches it; and laſtly has a ſuppreſſion of Urine: In this caſe I ſay I bleed more freely than before, and uſe Cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and cooling Medicines oftner, eſpecially in the Spring; and tho' this Symptom do not appear in young People, and in thoſe whoſe Blood is brisk, they admit of theſe Remedies without much hazard; and by the uſe of ſuch Remedies I endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to keep up the Patient, till the Diſeaſe has laſted a while, and then 'tis not very difficult to free him at once of the Symptom and the Diſeaſe too; and this may be done by giving ſome <hi>Narco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> Medicine in a large doſe; for tho' when the Fever is at the height thoſe things that are of a Narcotic quality do no good, nor anſwer the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians end, yet being given ſeaſonably at the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination of the Diſeaſe are very beneficial; but before they can do no good, partly becauſe they can't ſtop the force of Fermentation, tho' they are given in the largeſt doſe; and partly, which truly is moſt conſiderable, becauſe the Peccant matter at that time equally mixt with the Blood, and not yet tending to ſeparation is reſtrained by ſuch a Medicine, and ſo the deſpumation ſo much to be deſir'd is hinder'd; but whether this be the reaſon of this Phaenomenon, or ſome other more obſtruſe, let thoſe judge who have a mind and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:153471:30"/>
leaſure to think of ſuch things. But I declare that 'tis moſt certain, from a faithful and due col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of many obſervations, that <hi>Laudanum</hi> or any other Narcotics in the beginning, increaſe, or ſtate of this Fever does no good for the quelling of this Symptom, but as it often happens does harm; but in the declination of the Diſeaſe, 'tis us'd ſucceſsfully in a moderate Doſe. I once us'd a Narcotic on the twelfth day of the Diſeaſe not in vain, but I never knew it given ſooner with any ſucceſs; but if the uſe of it be deferr'd till the fourteenth day, 'twill do the better, ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on then being more perfect, neither indeed does this delay (tho' this dreadful Symptom does very much afrighten the by-ſtanders) preſently kill, for I have often obſerv'd, that it cou'd and was wont to bear a truce, till 'twas ſeaſonable to uſe Narcotics, if care was taken that the Intemperies begun, was not heighthen'd too much by <hi>Cordials</hi> and hot Medicines; in which caſe the Patient dies ſuddenly. The Narcotics which I am wont to uſe, are either <hi>London Laudanum,</hi> from one Grain to one Grain and a half, or the following,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take of Cowſlip flowers</hi> Mi, <hi>boyle them in a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient quantity of Black-Cherry water, diſſolve</hi> ℥ſſ, <hi>of Diacodium, and half a ſpoonful of juice of Lemons, in</hi> ℥iii <hi>of the ſtrain'd Liquor, mingle them. Or take of Black-Cherry water</hi> ℥iſſ, <hi>Epidemic water</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ii, <hi>Liquid Laudanum</hi> Gutt. xvi, <hi>Syrup of July flowers</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>i, <hi>mingle them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I will only add this, which I think is worth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, to wit, that if this Symptom will grant
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:153471:30"/>
a truce ſo long, and the Fever continues a long ſpace, ſo that the Patient may be ſafely purg'd before the taking of the <hi>Anodyne,</hi> 'twill prove more effectual, wherefore I us'd to order ℈ii, of the Pill <hi>Coch. major.</hi> diſſolv'd in Betony water ten or twelve hours before the taking of the Narco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic, neither is there any danger from the Tumult, which that hot Pill wou'd otherwiſe occaſion; for the vertue of the following Narcotic, will appeaſe thoſe commotions and eſtabliſh moſt gentle and ſweet peace.</p>
                  <p>But if the watchings continue after the Fever is gone off, all the other Symptoms being likewiſe ceas'd, I have obſerv'd that a rag dipt in Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, and apply'd cold to the fore part of the Head and Temples, is more beneficial than any Narcotic whatever.</p>
                  <p>It often happens that the Sick is vext with a Cough, through the whole courſe <note place="margin">A Cough.</note> of the Diſeaſe, to wit, the maſs of Blood being in a commotion, and raging violently; all things now tending to Sedition, it comes to paſs that the Humors let looſe and flowing from the maſs of Blood, by the veſſels of the Lungs, or alſo by an Apertion of them, are caſt upon the inner Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brane of the <hi>Aſpera Arteria,</hi> to wit, the thinner, being of exquiſite ſenſe; and hence the Cough ariſes, which is firſt dry, becauſe the matter being yet thin, fruſtrates the expulſive faculty, preſently it grows thick, and is difficultly Expectorated, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by degrees 'tis baked by the Febrile heat, and hence it comes to paſs that the Patient is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour ag'd by fear of choaking, becauſe he wants ſtrength to Cough up this viſcid matter. In this
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:153471:31"/>
caſe I rarely uſe any other Medicines than <hi>Oyl of Almonds</hi> freſh drawn, unleſs it happen (and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time 'tis ſo) that the Patient has wholly an aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to Oyl, and then we muſt uſe the common Pectorals; but I think Oyl of Almonds, if the Patient can bear it, is to be preferr'd before other Pectorals, for this reaſon chiefly, for that 'tis ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary they are given in a larger quantity if we do any thing to the purpoſe; and by this means we overcharge the Stomach which was too weak before, and inclined to be nauſeous; and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times alſo we are hindred upon the ſame account, ſo that we can't mind thoſe things which are to be diſpatch'd at the ſame time; neither can I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, nor learn by experience, why we ſhou'd ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from the uſe of this Oyl (which we have now mention'd) in Fevers, to wit, becauſe 'tis inflamable, and therefore to be fear'd leſt it ſhou'd increaſe the Fever; for ſuppoſe it naturally hot, yet certainly its heat is not ſo great, but that the advantage of it upon another account may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſate for it, for 'tis manifeſtly more Pectoral than other things, and opens and Lubricates the paſſages and promotes Expectoration, by which (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially if it happen to be large) the Blood is both freed from a troubleſom Humor, now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently evacuated and alſo ſomewhat cool'd. And therefore I am not much concern'd when at any time I perceive this Symptom intervenes, for by it the Patient is not a little relieved. I only admoniſh that 'tis not ſafe to give it at firſt by whole ſpoonfuls, for there is danger leſt it make the Stomach nauſeous and cauſe a looſneſs, and therefore 'tis to be given ſparingly and frequently
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:153471:31"/>
Night and Day, by which, Expectoration being made, the Cough is not only leſſen'd, but alſo which is of ſome moment, the Patients ſtrength worn out, is ſomewhat renewed with a gentle nouriſhment.</p>
                  <p>Sometimes it happens that an <hi>Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrhage</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">An Haemor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhage of the Noſe.</note> 
                     <hi>of the Noſe</hi> ſupervenes, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for that too hot Medicines were given at the beginning of the Diſeaſe, or that the Ebullition was not ſufficiently reſtrain'd, when the Patient was either in the flower of his Age, or the ſeaſon of the Year further'd it: If it happen ſo, thoſe things will do no great good, that are commonly us'd to ſtop the motion of the Blood, as Bleeding, Ligatures, Aſtringent and Agglun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinative Medicines, or thoſe things that attempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the Acrimony of the Blood, and the like. For tho' theſe and other ſuch things may be us'd according to the prudence and advice of Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, yet the main buſineſs is to bridle the Ebulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Blood, with ſome fit Medicine that may ſtop the force of it ruſhing upon every preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pice. Indeed if the Symptom be conſider'd apart, thoſe things which we have mention'd before, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially Bleeding, are proper enough; neither wou'd I doubt to uſe them, but truly they don't ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently anſwer the cauſe of this Symptom, at leaſt if you except Bleeding; and really 'tis as rational to endeavour with a Sword to put out Fire, as to take off this Symptom by the things above men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd. Therefore having try'd in vain other things in this caſe, I us'd to preſcribe ſome ſuch thing as follows.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:153471:32"/>
                     <hi>Take of Purſlain and Erratic Poppy water of each</hi> ℥iſſ, <hi>of Diacodium</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>vi, <hi>Syrup of Cowſlips</hi> ℥ſſ. <hi>mingle them for a draught.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I wou'd not have theſe things ſo underſtood, as if I wou'd preſently ſtop every <hi>Haemorrhage,</hi> for 'tis often rather to be permitted, for it may much relieve the patient, partly by ſuppreſſing too great an Ebullition, and ſometimes partly alſo by car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying off the Diſeaſe critically; and indeed 'tis to little purpoſe to uſe the foreſai'd remedy, for this Symptom before it has continued ſometime, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Vein has been open'd in the Arm. This is carefully to be noted, that this and all other im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate <hi>Haemorrhages</hi> have this peculiar to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that aſſoon as they are ſtopt, by what means ſoever it be, the Patient is in danger of a relapſe, if ſome lenitive Purge be not given; and therefore we muſt Purge, tho' (with reſpect to the ſeaſon of the Fever) it is wont and ought to be put off ſomewhat longer unleſs this Symptom hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen.</p>
                  <p>This Symptom for the moſt part hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens <note place="margin">The Hickock.</note> to old Men, after large Evacuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, either by a Looſneſs, or eſpecially by Vomit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it very often portends that death is near at hand. I ingenuouſly confeſs, that I can't ſatisfie my ſelf in my ſearch after the Cauſe of the <hi>Hic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kocks;</hi> yet I have often obſerv'd they take their riſe from a diſturbance in the Stomach or neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring parts, rais'd by rough Medicines, for the quelling and reducing of which to priſtine peace when the ſtrength of Nature is not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, there is great imminent Danger; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:153471:32"/>
I have thought it reaſonable to provide for it, that what Nature cou'd not do of her ſelf, ſhe ſhou'd do by the aſſiſtance of Art. Therefore ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given a large doſe, (to wit two Drams) of <hi>Diaſcordium,</hi> it has done the buſineſs, when I cou'd do not good with the Seeds of Dill, and other things that are cry'd up as Specifics.</p>
                  <p>If in the courſe of this Diſeaſe a looſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <note place="margin">A Diarrhaea.</note> ariſe, which (as we have noted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove) us'd to happen, when a Vomit was indica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at the beginning of the Diſeaſe, and was not taken. In this caſe I ſay a Vomit may be given at any time of the Diſeaſe, if the Strength does not Contraindicat, tho' the inclination to Vomiting be long ſince paſs'd. But becauſe I think I have Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſufficiently of this thing in the former Pages, I will only add this now, to wit, what is to be done if a looſneſs come, tho' a Vomit has been given, which indeed is very rare unleſs in an Inflamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Fever, where a Vomit does not only hinder this Symptom, but ſometimes occaſion it, which muſt be obſerv'd; therefore when things are ſo I have found a Clyſter of this kind more beneficial than any other Aſtringent whatever.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take of the Bark of Pomegranates</hi> ℥ſſ, <hi>of Red Roſes</hi> Pii, <hi>boyle them in a ſufficient quantity of Cows Milk, diſſolve</hi> ℥ſſ <hi>of Diaſcordium in half a pound of the ſtrain'd Liquor, mingle them and make a Clyſter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I would not adviſe that a Clyſter ſhou'd be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected in a greater quantity, for tho' it may be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally Aſtringent, yet there is danger leſt it
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:153471:33"/>
ſhou'd weary the Inteſtines by its bulk, and ſo provoke more the flux which we endeavour to ſtop.</p>
                  <p>But perhaps ſome one will object that it ſeems more proper, eſpecially at the declination of the Diſeaſe, that the <hi>Diarrhaea</hi> if it happen, ſhou'd ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be permitted than ſtopt, for as much as that Flux is ſometimes critical, and carries off the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe: I anſwer, that I don't deny, but that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the Fever is carried off this way, but this ſo ſeldom happens that we may not depend upon it, and that account (in which having ſpoke generally of the Cure of all Fevers, we endeavoured to prove the neceſſity of the ſtopping this Flux) is alſo here much to the purpoſe; and now this is to be added, and in my Opinion 'tis worth obſerving, to wit, that for a genuine Depuration of the Blood, 'tis not only neceſſary that there be a Secretion of ſome parts by the <hi>Faeces,</hi> but it is requiſite alſo that others like <hi>Flowers</hi> be ſeparated, which is daily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd in other Rich and Heterogenious Liquors; wherefore if we too much indulge the <hi>Diarrhaea,</hi> the Depuration ſo much deſir'd wou'd be only im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, and perchance that which ſhou'd be caſt out laſt wou'd be Secreted firſt. Truly I confeſs that ſeparation by Flowers being made (which by the by is perform'd gradually and inſenſibly, and more commonly by large perſpiration rather than by manifeſt ſweat) the <hi>Diarrhaea</hi> if it ſhou'd chance to happen will not be very dangerous; but 'tis to be noted that then it happens upon no other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, but becauſe purging to carry off the <hi>Faeces</hi> was not opportunely preſcrib'd, which <hi>Faeces</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed by their continuance growing malignant,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:153471:33"/>
provoke now the Inteſtines to Excretion; to ſay nothing that that Liquid conſiſtence of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements, (for ſo they are moſt commonly) ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently indicates, that 'tis not to be accounted a critical Solution of the Diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>And perchance the <hi>Iliac Paſſion</hi> may be reckon'd among the Symptoms that come <note place="margin">The Iliac Paſſion.</note> upon Fevers, becauſe violent Vomitings, which are wont to appear at the beginning of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, ſometimes occaſion it.</p>
                  <p>This dreadful Diſeaſe, being hitherto almoſt in the opinion of all mortal, takes its riſe from the inverted, and prepoſterous motion of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtines. To wit, the Fibres of the Inteſtines, which ought to be contracted from the Superior to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Inferiour, are drawn to the Superior; and whatſoever is contained in the Inteſtines, is not protruded to the Belly, but towards the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, and is violently regurgitated to the mouth; ſo that Clyſters, how ſharp ſoever, become vomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive; and alſo Cathartics, taken by the mouth, are ſuddenly caſt up by Vomit: And in my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the exquiſit and intollerable pain coming up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Diſeaſe, is only occaſioned by the foreſaid prepoſterous motion of the Inteſtines. For whereas thoſe Folds which the many circumvolutions of the Inteſtines make, are ſo form'd by Nature, that they ſhould moſt fitly conduce to the carrying down of the Faeces, when they, I ſay, are forc'd to give way to a motion contrary to their Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres, the aforeſaid pain is occaſion'd from thence, which is fixed to one part, and is like the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of an Auger, when either the Valve, which is placed at the beginning of the Colon, hinders the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153471:34"/>
going back of the Excrements to the Ileon, or any other Membrane belonging to the <hi>Sinus,</hi> ſuſtains alone the force of this prepoſterous Impulſe.</p>
                  <p>We may aſſign a two-fold cauſe of this Inver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, from whence that pain ariſes, <hi>viz.</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and Irritation.</p>
                  <p>Firſt therefore, whatever violently obſtructs the Inteſtines, ſo that nothing can paſs down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, neceſſarily produces this contrary motion in them. Among theſe, Authors are wont to reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Excrements harden'd, groſs wind collected in a great quantity, and tying up as it were the Inteſtines, the conſtriction of them in a Rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and laſtly, an Inflammation, and other great Tumours which ſtop up the internal Cavity of the Inteſtine. In the mean time we muſt not deny, that this contrary motion, owing its riſe to theſe cauſes, is rather to be accounted the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the things taken in, than of the Inteſtines: Neither is this an inverſion of the whole duct of the Inteſtines, but only of thoſe which are ſituated above the ſeat of that obſtruction; wherefore I call an <hi>Iliac Paſſion</hi> proceeding hence, <hi>Spurious.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, I think that in the <hi>Iliac Paſſion</hi> the cauſe of the inverſion of the <hi>periſtaltic</hi> motion of the Inteſtines, is moſt commonly after this manner, <hi>viz.</hi> Sharp and malignant humours are caſt upon the Stomach, and the Guts that are next to it, by the Blood raging on the account of the Fever begun of late, by which the motion of the Stomach is firſt inverted, and forc'd vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently to caſt up what is contained in it; at length the ſmall guts that are join'd to the Stomach be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing weakned, yield to the violent motion of it, and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:153471:34"/>
with them at laſt the greater follow by conſent, the Stomach vomiting, leading as it were the Dance. This I call the true <hi>Iliac Paſſion,</hi> and which is treated of now: The Method of curing, it has been hitherto in a manner unknown, whatever ſome boaſt of the uſe of <hi>Quick-ſilver</hi> and <hi>Bullets,</hi> which beſides that they do little good, are oft very injurious. I have ſucceſsfully us'd this method.</p>
                  <p>When it appears by Clyſters caſt up by the mouth, and other ſigns, that 'tis a true <hi>Iliac Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> I endeavour theſe three things: Firſt, That the contrary motion of the Stomach, which cauſes the like motion of the Guts, may be hindred. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, That the Inteſtines being weakned by the ſharp humour, may be corroborated. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That the Stomach and Guts be freed from thoſe Humours; and that I may anſwer theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dications, I inſtitute the Cure after this manner: Firſt, I preſcribe one Scruple of <hi>Salt</hi> of <hi>Wormwood</hi> in a ſpoonful of <hi>Juice of Lemons</hi> to be taken morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and evening: But at other times of the day I order ſome ſpoonfuls of Mint-water without Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, or any thing elſe to be taken twice in an hour, by the repeated uſe of which alone, the vomiting, and the pain ariſing from thence will ſoon vaniſh. At the ſame time I order a live Kitling to lie continually upon the naked Belly: But after the pain and vomiting has wholly ceas'd for the ſpace of two or three days, <hi>I give one Dram of the Pill Coch. Maj. diſſolved in Mint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water,</hi> which I alſo order to be us'd very often all the time of the working of the Pills, that I may the more certainly hinder the return of the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting: Neither is the Kitling to be remov'd before the Patient has taken the Pills.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:153471:35"/>
I have obſerv'd that 'tis to no purpoſe to give theſe Pills, or any other Cathartics, how ſtrong ſoever, until the Stomach is ſtrengthned, and reduced to its natural motion, and the Guts alſo to that which is proper to them: For otherwiſe all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thartics taken inwardly would prove <hi>emetic,</hi> and ſo do more hurt than good; and therefore I don't uſe purging Medicines, until for ſome time I have us'd thoſe Medicines which reſpect the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach.</p>
                  <p>I preſcribe a very thin Diet, for I allow only ſome ſpoonfuls of Chicken broath to be taken twice or thrice a day; in the mean while I order the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient to keep his bed all the time of the Sickneſs, till the ſigns of perfect health appear; and when he is well I appoint him to perſiſt in the uſe of the foreſaid water, for a long time, and to keep his Belly warm with Flannels doubl'd, that there may not be a relapſe, to which this Diſeaſe is more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious than any other.</p>
                  <p>My whole method of Curing this Diſeaſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts of theſe few things, which I truſt will not be deſpis'd by any Judicious Perſon, by reaſon of its ſimplicity, and want of Rhetorick, and pomp of Medicines. And theſe are the Symptoms that are wont to happen in this Fever, there are ſome others which I will not now mention, partly becauſe they are of leſs moment, and partly becauſe they don't require a peculiar way of Cure, for the Fever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well treated they go off of themſelves. And ſo much for the continual Fever of this Conſtitution and of its Symptoms.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:153471:35"/>
                  <head>CHAP. II. Of the New Fever.</head>
                  <p>THO my old Age, worn out almoſt by long Sickneſs, may well require on that account a Writ of Eaſe, and a ceſſation from deep thought, the labour of the Brain; yet I cou'd not forbear, but I muſt be buſi'd in the procuring the Health of others, tho even by the loſs of my own; when my acquaintance inform'd me of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of a new Conſtitution, from whence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded a new ſort of Fever, much unlike thoſe that reign'd of late.</p>
                  <p>We muſt remember that in <hi>Autumn</hi> 1677. Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittent Fevers firſt advanc'd and increas'd dayly, and were Epidemic till they came to their ſtate; afterwards they gradually decreas'd and ſo rarely appear'd the laſt Years of this Conſtitution, that they cou'd not be 'counted Epidemical; and on this account we muſt likewiſe take notice that the two laſt Years of the Conſtitution now going off, had two very ſevere Winters, eſpecially the laſt ſave one, <hi>viz.</hi> the Year 1683, in which the ſeaſon was ſo extreamly cold, that no Man living ever ſaw the like, as to the intenſe degree of cold, and the long time it held. For the Noble River of <hi>Thames</hi> was ſo froze that it eaſily ſuſtain'd, like a ſolid pavement, Coaches running about upon it, and Shops well ſtock'd, in the manner of Streets, and great crowds of People. Tho the following Year 84, did not equal the preceding, either as to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:153471:36"/>
the extremity of cold or obſtinate duration of it, yet it did not come much behind it as to either; but as ſoon as it thaw'd in <hi>February,</hi> in the Year 8 4/5. this Fever, began that I now treat of, which I take to be a new ſort of Fever, and wholly diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from that which has prevail'd for theſe eight Years laſt paſt.</p>
                  <p>I can't certainly ſay whether the change of this Conſtitution is to be attributed to the alteration of the manifeſt qualities of the Air, which ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded for thoſe two Winters; for I have obſerv'd that alterations as to the ſenſible qualities of Years how different ſoever, have not produc'd ſpecies of Epidemic Diſeaſes; and that a certain ſeries of Years (tho one Year has differ'd from another, as to outward appearance and temperament) have notwithſtanding all agreed in the production of the ſame ſpecies of ſtationary Fevers; which when I had ſeriouſly conſider'd, I was of the Opinion, as I have mention'd in another place, that the change of a Conſtitution chiefly depends on ſome ſecret and hidden alteration in the Bowels of the Earth paſſing through the whole Atmoſphaere, or from ſome influence of the Coeleſtial Bodies. Tho 'tis to be noted here, that when the Depuratory Fever here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore went off, a very dry and violent Froſt from the beginning of Winter 64, froze up all things, nor did it at all abate till the beginning of <hi>March,</hi> at which time, aſſoon as the Froſt went off, and a Peſtilential Fever, ſoon after the Plague be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to rage. But however this be, the Fever which we now Treat of, began at the time afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, to wit in <hi>Feb.</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. and was more ſpread through all the parts of <hi>England,</hi> and more Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demic
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:153471:36"/>
in other places than here in <hi>London,</hi> the Year before and this Year.</p>
                  <p>When I was firſt call'd to this Fever, I verily believ'd 'twas not of that kind of Fevers which I call Stationary, but rather of the Family of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercurrents, which come promiſcuouſly almoſt in all Years; to wit, that 'twas nothing elſe than that Baſtard <hi>Peripneumonia,</hi> which I have hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſcrib'd in my Book of Acute Diſeaſes, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with this difference, that in this Fever the Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptoms did not appear now and then, which were more Pathognomonic in the <hi>Peripneumonia;</hi> ſuch are a violent Cough, a violent Head-ach in Cough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, cleaving as it were the Head, a Giddineſs upon any motion, and a great difficulty in Breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, all which did moſt commonly accompany the Baſtard <hi>Peripneumonia.</hi> When therefore the Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller deſir'd a new Edition of my Works at that time, I Publiſh'd my conjecture in the Poſtſcript, in which I perceive I was miſtaken; and truly I was led into this Error by the great and manifeſt agreement which was between this Fever and the foreſaid <hi>Peripneumonia,</hi> which comes now and then every Winter; but the Summer coming on, which was wont to vanquiſh theſe <hi>Peripneumonic</hi> Fevers, and this notwithſtanding continuing, I was ſoon convinc'd of my error, and was wholly perſuaded that 'twas to be reduc'd to a new Conſtitution.</p>
                  <p>After as diligent a ſearch as I cou'd make, the <hi>Symptoms</hi> I obſerv'd are, and were for the moſt part theſe, the Sick is Cold and Hot by turns, and often complains of Pain of his Head and Limbs; the Pulſe are like the Pulſe of thoſe that are well; Blood taken away is moſt commonly like the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:153471:37"/>
Blood of Pleuritics; the Patient for the moſt part is troubl'd with a Cough, which together with other Symptoms accompanying a gentle <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ripneumonia</hi> goes off ſo much the ſooner, by how much longer the Diſeaſe invades from Winter. A pain ſeizes the Neck and Jaws, ſometimes at the beginning of the Diſeaſe, but 'tis leſs than in a Quinſey; tho the Fever be Continual, yet it has of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten violent Exacerbations towards Evening, as if 'twere a double Tertian or Quotidian. The Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent is much endanger'd by keeping his Bed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, tho he has but very little clothes on, for by that means the Fever being turn'd upon the Brain he ſoon falls into a <hi>Coma</hi> or Frenſie; and to ſpeak the truth, the inclination in this Diſeaſe to a Frenſie is ſo great that it often creeps on of a ſudden of its own accord, without any ſuch occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. But the Frenſie does not riſe with ſo great a fury in this Fever, as in that with which thoſe that have the Small Pox and other Fevers are ſeiz'd; for the Sick rather doats, muttering now and then ſome odd words. Petechiae very often break out by reaſon of the unſeaſonable uſe of Cordials, and too a hot Regimen; and in young People of a hot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, Purple Spots the certain ſigns of a high Inflammation, as well in this as in any other kind of Acute Diſeaſes; and ſometimes Eruptions which they call Miliares, ſprinkle themſelves over the Superficies of the Body, and are not much unlike the Meaſles, only they are Redder, and when they go off they don't leave behind them thoſe Branny Scales which are ſeen in the Meaſles; tho they come ſometimes of their own accord, yet moſt commonly they are forc'd out by the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:153471:37"/>
heat of the Bed and Cordials. The Patients' Tongue is either moiſt or dry according to the Method which has been us'd; when its dry 'tis of a Duskiſh Colour in the middle, which is hemm'd round with a whitiſh Fringe; but when 'tis moiſt 'tis all White, cover'd alſo with a White and filthy Skin; for if the Patient be too much heated by the Method us'd, the Tongue is moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Dusky and Dry, but if not 'tis Moiſt and White. The ſame is to be affirm'd of Sweat, which flows according to the different Method a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid; for if the Patient be treated with too much Heat, 'tis in a manner Viſcous, eſpecially about the Head; and tho it flow freely, and from all parts, yet the Sick has little relief by it: ſo that 'tis manifeſt that ſuch Sweats are only Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptomatical; not Critical. Sweat forc'd by Art at the beginning of the Diſeaſe, us'd to put off the Morbific matter, if not on the Head, at leaſt upon the Limbs. But when the Fever has poſſeſs'd the Head, and the Frenſre has once prevail'd, then no ſigns of the Fever remain, only the Pulſe is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times quicker ſometimes ſlower: but at length, when by ill management, the Spirits are driven into a Confuſion, the Pulſe is inordinate, with a <hi>Subſultus</hi> of the Members, and Death ſoon fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows.</p>
                  <p>As to the Cure, thoſe Signs of the Peripneu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monia which accompanied this Fever laſt Year in <hi>February,</hi> in which it firſt began, made me believe preſently after Winter, as I ſaid before, that it ought to be reckon'd with the Family of Peripneu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monics; and therefore I preſently betook my ſelf to that Method which I have heretofore commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:153471:38"/>
in the Cure of the Baſtard <hi>Peripneumonia,</hi> which indeed was very ſuccesful to me, in thoſe few, I was ſcarce able to take care of by reaſon of my Sickneſs, and to others who were pleas'd to try it upon my commendation. What ever it was that perſuaded me to uſe this Method, I am now fully ſatisfied, having weigh'd the <hi>Phaenomena</hi> of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, and the Temperateneſs of the laſt Year, which follow'd the two cold Winters (eſpecially of the Winter, if it cou'd be call'd ſo, for it brought with it no conſiderable cold) I ſay 'tis manifeſt to me that this Fever is nothing elſe than a ſimple Inflammation of the Blood, and that therefore the Curative Indications are wholly to be directed to the ſuppreſſing of the ſaid Inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation by proper Remedies and Methods.</p>
                  <p>Therefore I proceed after this manner, firſt I order ten ounces of Blood to be taken from the Arm; and truly this Fever (how like ſoever the Blood be moſt commonly to that of Pleuritics) does not eaſily bear repeated Bleeding; but if a diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of Breathing, a lancing pain of the Head in Coughing and the like, ſignifie that this Diſeaſe tends to a Baſtard <hi>Peripneumonia,</hi> then Bleeding and Purging are to be repeated, until all the Symptoms wholly vaniſh, as I have ſaid in the Chapter of a <hi>Peripneumonia,</hi> and I deſire this may be ſeriouſly minded.</p>
                  <p>In the Evening I apply a Bliſter to the Pole, and next Morning give this lenitive Portion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take of Tamarinds</hi> ℥ſſ, <hi>leaves of Senna</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ii, <hi>Rubarb</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>iſſ, <hi>boyl them in a ſufficient quantity of water to</hi> ℥iii, <hi>in the ſtrain'd Liquor, diſſolve
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:153471:38"/>
of Manna and Syrup of Roſes Solutive each</hi> ℥i,, <hi>mingle them and make a Potion to be taken early in the Morning.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which I order to be repeated every other day for thrice, and this or the like Paregoric to be taken at Bed-time after every Purge.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take of Cowſlip water</hi> ℥ii, <hi>of Diacodium</hi> ℥i, <hi>of juice of Lemons freſhdrawn 2 ſpoonfuls, mingle them and make a draught.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>viz.</hi> To prevent the Patients being Comatoſe, by reaſon of the confuſion of the Animal Spirits, which Purges often occaſion, by the Tumult they raiſe in the Blood and Humours of thoſe that have Fevers; which Symptom is Cru'd by Hypnotic Medicines, tho they ſeem to promote it; for which reaſon not daring to give a Purge, in the Comatoſe Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of the Year 73. I perſiſted in the uſe of Cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; for I knew very well that Purging Medicines, us'ed at that time, preſently occaſion'd a Coma, which perhaps wou'd have happen'd otherwiſe, if I had thought of giving a Paregonic after ſuch a Purge. But when the Patient does not Purge, we muſt not give an Anodyne at bed-time, leſt it hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the operation of the Cathartic, which is to be taken the next day (which is uſual, tho it be taken late) but if it don't wholly ſtop it, it will render it leſs efficacious. 'Tis a Rule with me, in this and other Epidemic Fevers, not to Purge either in the beginning or ſtate of the Diſeaſe, unleſs Bleeding hath firſt been us'd: which indeed by being either neglected or violated has occaſion'd the Death of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:153471:39"/>
many, eſpecially of Children, as I have in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place admoniſh'd by way of caution.</p>
                  <p>But we muſt take notice, that tho for the moſt part the 'foreſaid Evacuations ought to be us'd in the Cure of this Fever, yet often the Sick, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if he be a young Man or Infant, preſently recovers after Bleeding and being once Purg'd: and there is no occaſion for more, the Fever being vanquiſh'd by the firſt; but on the contrary 'tis ſometimes neceſſary that Purges ſhou'd be us'd oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner than we ſaid before. For it ſometimes hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens, tho rarely, that the Patient being freed by this Method, relapſes in a few days after by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Febrile matter growing Crude again; but 'tis preſently Eliminated by the Purge repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the fourth time, tho this Fever ſeldom happens under this Method, unleſs it be occaſion'd by <hi>Aph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thae,</hi> coming at the latter end of the preceding Fever, and now being at their heigth, recall it; which Fever is indeed only Symptomatical, and the Hickocks returning by intervals often follow it, which alſo remain for ſome days after the Fever is gone off; but at length vaniſh of their own accord, as the Patient gets ſtrength, which is diligently to be noted; for as much as there is no danger from the <hi>Hickocks</hi> coming at the latter end of this Fever, unleſs many Medicines are over officiouſly and unprofitably cramm'd in, and then Death is inſtead of the Phyſitian; but both the <hi>Aphthae</hi> and <hi>Hickocks,</hi> or either of them, if they don't go off of their own accord, but continue a long while, may be eaſily Cur'd by the Peruvian Bark, <hi>viz.</hi> an ounce with a ſufficient quantity of Erratic Poppies, either in the form of an Electu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:153471:39"/>
or Pills taken after the manner I ſet down heretofore in my Epiſtle to Dr. <hi>Brady,</hi> drinking upon it a draught of Poſſet-drink. Which Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy I have found by experience in this caſe more certain than any other whatever, if its vertue be not ſpoyl'd (as commonly 'tis) by the Patient keeping his Bed continually.</p>
                  <p>I ſometimes preſcribe the following or the like, on the days the Purges are not taken.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take of the Conſerve of Wood-ſorrel, of Cynosbal. <abbr>aa</abbr>
                     </hi> ℥i, <hi>Conſerve of Barberies</hi> ℥ſſ, <hi>Cream of Tartar</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>i, <hi>with a ſufficient quantity of Syrup of Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, make an Electuary, of which take the quantity of a Nutmeg thrice aday, drinking upon it four ſpoonfuls of the following Julap.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take of the water of Purſlain, Lettice and Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlips <abbr>aa</abbr>
                     </hi> ℥iii, <hi>of Syrup of Lemons</hi> ℥iſſ, <hi>of Syrup of Violets</hi> ℥i, <hi>mingle them and make a Julap.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Or take of Fountain waters</hi> 
                     <abbr>lb</abbr>i, <hi>of Roſe water, of the juice of Lemons, of White Sugar</hi> 
                     <abbr>aa</abbr> ℥iv, <hi>boyl them over a gentle fire, till all the ſcum be riſen, take</hi> ℥iii <hi>at pleaſure.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But in all theſe things I forbear the uſe of <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> of <hi>Vitriol,</hi> tho it be very refrigerating, becauſe 'tis not proper in any Diſeaſes that are Cur'd by Purging, by reaſon 'tis ſo very Styptick, not to mention now the Mineral nature of this Spirit.</p>
                  <p>It often happens, eſpecially towards the end of this Fever, that the Sick when he is mannag'd after this manner, Sweats now and then of his
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:153471:40"/>
own accord in the Night, by which all the Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptoms of the Diſeaſe are very much mitigated; but notwithſtanding ſeeing we can't truſt in ſuch Sweats, we muſt by no means intermit the 'fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid method, becauſe if the Sick ſhou'd indulge thoſe Sweats for a longer time, the Fever which the preceding Purges had in ſome ſort ſubjugated wou'd again revive; for if the Sweat be protract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed beyond that time, in which the Febrile par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles repair'd by due coction are wholly carried off, the Sweats that follow do nothing elſe but kindle the flame afreſh; wherfore tho thoſe Sweats which flowed Spontaneouſly were perchance critical, with reſpect to the caſting out of the Febrile matter, which is fit for Expulſion, yet the others that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them may be only Symptomatical, and ſo do more hurt than good. In a word, the gentle heat of the Bed at Nights opportunely favours ſuch Sweats as flow of their own accord in the Night; wherefore the Sick ſhou'd have no more nor thicker clothes on, than he uſe to have when he was well, nor ſhou'd any hot Medicines be given. Let him only keep his Bed a little longer than he is wont, in the Morning following, and afterwards let him perſiſt in the method of Cure above preſcrib'd.</p>
                  <p>His diet is to be Oatmeal and Barly broaths, and now and then a roaſted Apple, and after the ſecond Purge Chicken broath. I order ſmall Beer cold for his ordinary drink, and the white Decocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made of one ounce of Harts-horn calcind, and boyl'd in three pints of common water, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſweeten'd with white Sugar.</p>
                  <p>Tis not neceſſary, as I have mention'd in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, after the taking of two Purges, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:153471:40"/>
the Eating of Chickens, and the like of eaſie concoction; for this way of Cure by Purging in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulges the ſame, which cou'd not be allow'd if we proceeded in another way; moreover after the laſt Purge, if the Fever has a little ſpent it ſelf, and is not yet turn'd to an Ague, three or four ſpoonfuls of Canary Wine may be taken Night and Morning, and after Dinner for ſome Days, by which the Strength may be the ſooner reſtor'd and the Febrile fits averted.</p>
                  <p>But for as much as this kind of Fever is more prone, than any other I ever yet ſaw, to aſſault the Head, neither can it be remov'd from thence with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great difficulty: I ſeriouſly admoniſh my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients that they lye a Bed naked only a Nights, but if they are ſo very much weaken'd that they can't ſit upright, I permit that they ſhou'd lye upon the Bed or Couch with their clothes on, with their Heads a little elevated; neither do I allow that they ſhou'd have any more fire in their Chambers than when they were well.</p>
                  <p>And as this Regimen is to be obſerv'd from the beginning, in all that are ſeiz'd with this Fever, (excepting Women taken on the firſt days of Childbed) ſo is it neceſſarily enjoin'd, when the Phyſitian is call'd to a Patient, who by reaſon of too hot a Regimen, has been ſeiz'd with a Phrenſie, Petechiae or Purple ſpots, or any other ſigns of a violent inflammation; for in this caſe tho Blood be taken away, tho the Body be lightly cover'd, and whatever cooling Liquors are drunk, yet the Fever will not ceaſe till the Patient keeps from bed adays, for as much as the heat of the Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Air, kept in by the coverings, too much exagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:153471:41"/>
the Blood, and the lying poſture of the Body forces the ſame with violence on the Head; but when the Phrenſie hath once prevail'd, by reaſon of an ill Method, it can't preſently be tamed, neither is it ſafe to endeavour the Cure by repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Bleeding and purging beyond the limits pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd; but at length 'twill go off at its own time and of its own accord, by the help of the Method aforeſaid. But nothing ſo much conduces to the removal of it as ſhaving the Head, and therefore I always order it without applying a Plaiſter, only a Cap ſo thick as may compenſate the loſs of the Hair, or at leaſt defend the Head from external cold; by this means the Brain is very much cool'd and refreſh'd, ſo that by degrees it may be able to overcome the hot impreſſions that occaſion the Phrenſie.</p>
                  <p>And what has been ſaid of a Phrenſie may like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be affirm'd of the Coma that comes upon this Fever, in which and in the ſaid Phrenſie the Febrile matter is carried up to the Head, and ſo if you except the whiteneſs of the Tongue there are no ſigns of a Fever; for the Patient ſeems to be wholly freed from it. In this Sympton as in the other, Cathartics, Sudorifics, Bliſters, and the like, are not us'd only unſucceſsfully, but do a great deal of hurt; for ſuch Evacuation procure death, ſooner than the Cure of this Symptom: wherefore after general Evacuations, by Bleeding and Purging, the buſineſs is to be committed to Nature and time, tho this Symptom terrifie the by-ſtanders; for tho the Sick be ſtupid for a long time, yet he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover his Health after many days, if he be not continually kept a Bed; but is taken out of it a
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:153471:41"/>
days and laid upon a Couch, or on the Bed with his Clothes on; in the mean time his Head may be ſhav'd, and at the latter end of this Symptom three or four ſpoonfuls of Canary Wine may be given twice a day. But I have Treated largely of this in the fifth Section, and ſecond Chapter, of my Book of Acute Diſeaſes, where I diſcours'd of a certain notable <hi>Coma</hi> that accompanied that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution.</p>
                  <p>But as to the Fever the Phyſitian is not to be deterr'd, from making the 'foreſaid Evacuations, if upon feeling the Pulſe, he ſhou'd perceive a twitching of the Members or a Convulſive moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Body; for as much as in ſome kind of Diſeaſes of the Nerves, both Bleeding and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging don't only not do hurt but are neceſſarily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd; of which I will produce an experiment I made in a certain kind of Convulſion, which is commonly call'd <hi>Chorea Sancti Viti,</hi> of which Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe I have ſeen and Cur'd no leſs than Five by Bleeding and Purging preſcrib'd by intervals; of which ſort of Diſeaſe I will ſpeak ſomewhat ſeeing it occurs opportunely, and clearly confirms the truth of what I now aſſert. <hi>Chorea Sancti Viti,</hi> is a ſort of Convulſion which cheifly invades Boyes and Girles from ten Years of age to Puberity: Firſt it ſhews it ſelf by a certain Lameneſs, or rather inſtability of one of the Legs, which the Patient drags after him like a Fool, afterwards 'tis perceiv'd in the Hand of the ſame ſide, which he that has this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe can in no wiſe keep in the ſame poſture for a moment, if it be brought to the Breaſt or any other part, but 'twill be diſtorted to another poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or place by a certain Convulſion, do the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:153471:42"/>
what he can: if a cup of Drink be put in his Hand he repreſents a thouſand geſtures, like Juglers, before he brings it to his Mouth; for whereas he can't carry it to his Mouth in a right line, his Hand being drawn hither and thither by the Convulſion, he turns it often about for ſome time, till at length happily reaching his Lips he flings it ſuddenly into his Mouth, and drinks it greedily as if the poor wretch deſign'd only to make ſport. For as much as this Diſeaſe ſeems to me to proceed from ſome Humour ruſhing in upon the Nerves, which provokes ſuch preternatural motions; I think the Curative indications are firſt to be directed to the leſſening thoſe Humours by Bleeding and Purging, and then to the ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ening the <hi>genus nervoſum,</hi> in order to which I uſe this Method: I take ſeven ounces of Blood from the Arm, more or leſs according to the age of the Patient; the next day I preſcribe half or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more (according to the age, or the more or leſs diſpoſition of the Body to bear Purging) of the common Purging Potion above deſcrib'd, of Tamarinds, and Senna, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the Evening I give the following draught.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take of Black-Cherry water</hi> ℥i, <hi>of Langius's Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leptic water</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>iii, <hi>of old Venice Treacle</hi> ℈i, <hi>of liquid Laudanum</hi> Gutt. viii, <hi>make a draught.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I order the Purging Potion to be repeated thrice, once every other day, and a Paregoric draught the ſame nights; afterwards I preſcribe Bleeding and Purging as before, and ſo Alternately I Bleed and Purge till the Patient has Bled three or four
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:153471:42"/>
times, and after every Bleeding Purge ſo often as his ſtrength will bear; only it muſt be diligently obſerv'd that there muſt be ſo much ſpace between the Evacuations that the Patient receives no da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage from thence; if the days Purging is not us'd, I preſcribe as follows.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take of Conſerve of Roman Wormwood, of the Yellow rinde of Orranges</hi> 
                     <abbr>aa</abbr> ℥i, <hi>Conſerve of Roſemary Flowers</hi> ℥ſſ, <hi>of old Venice Treacle and Nutmegs Candid</hi> 
                     <abbr>aa</abbr> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>iii, <hi>of Ginger Candid</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>i, <hi>Syrup of the juice of Citrons a ſufficient quantity, make an Electuary, of which take the quantity of a Nutmeg in the Morning, and at five of the Clock in the Evening; drinking upon it five ſpoonfuls of the following Wine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take of the Roots of Paeony, Elicampane, Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort, Angelica</hi> 
                     <abbr>aa</abbr> ℥i, <hi>of the Leaves of Rue, Sage, Betony, Germander, white Whore-Hound, and the tops of the leſſer Centaury</hi> 
                     <abbr>aa</abbr> Mi, <hi>of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niper Berries</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>vi, <hi>the rinds of two Oranges; let them be cut and infus'd cold, in ſix pints of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary wine; ſtrain it as you uſe it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take of Rue water</hi> ℥iv, <hi>of Langius's Epileptic wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and compound Briony water</hi> 
                     <abbr>aa</abbr> ℥i, <hi>Syrup of Paeony</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>vi, <hi>mingle them and make a Julap, take four ſpoonfuls at bed-time, with eight drops of Spirit of Harts-horn. Let a Blaiſter of Gum Caranna be apply'd to the Soles of the Feet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The more the Patient recovers, the leſs he drags his Foot, and the Hand is ſteddier, ſo that he can
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:153471:43"/>
bring the cup to his Mouth more directly; which are certain ſigns how much better he is: but tho to perfect the Cure, I wou'd not adviſe that he ſhou'd be Bled more than three or four times, yet Cathartic, and Alterative Medicines are to be us'd till he is quite well. And becauſe he that has once this Diſeaſe may eaſily relapſe, I think it expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent that he be Blooded and Purg'd for ſome days the next year about the ſame time, or a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Diſeaſe firſt invaded. And truly I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that the <hi>Epilepſie of the adult,</hi> may go nigh to be Cur'd by this Method, if the Remedies preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed were well proportion'd to their Age, tho by reaſon I have ſeldom met with this Diſeaſe, I have not yet try'd it; but this by the by.</p>
                  <p>It ſometimes happens in Women ſubject to Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteric fits, that when the Cure has been managed by the 'foreſaid Evacuations, the Fever continues after Bleeding and Purging, tho repeated; in this caſe the Fever that now prevails is plainly continu'd by the commotion of the Spirits occaſion'd by the Evacuations; and therefore all other things being omitted, the Curative indications are only to be directed to the appeaſing the fury of the Spirits, if there be no ſigns of a Peripneumonia, or Inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation about the vital parts. In order to which a Paregoric, that is ſufficient to cauſe ſleep, ought to be preſcrib'd every night; and alſo Hyſteric Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines properly ſo call'd, twice or thrice a day, ſuch are Pills made of Galbanum, Aſſafetida, Caſtor and the like, and Julaps of the ſame nature, deſcrib'd in my Treatiſe of Hyſteric Fits. Moreover that meat and drink which is moſt agreeable to the appetite of the Patient ought to be allow'd to
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:153471:43"/>
recover the ſtrength, and to ſuppreſs the vapours, as they call them.</p>
                  <p>We have ſaid already, that this Fever had both the laſt year, and eſpecially this, a certain Exacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation dayly about night, not much unlike the fit of an intermittent Fever. Wherefore thoſe Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians that had found by experience that all thoſe Fevers which did any whit intermit (and oft thoſe that did not intermit at all) through that ſeries of years from 77 to the beginning of 85, were cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly Cur'd by the Peruvian Bark, treated this Fever with the ſame Remedy: but tho 'twas rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal, yet moſt commonly 'twas not ſo ſucceſsful as in the former years. For upon a diligent ſearch I found that tho a great quantity of the Bark was given, yet it rarely Cur'd the Patient, and ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rarely, that I rather imputed the recovery of the Sick to ſome lucky event of the Diſeaſe, than to the vertue of the Bark, ſo that it wholly loſt that Sanative vertue and certainty it had in the 'foreſaid years. I mean the Fever we Treat of now, which is ſomething like a Quotidian; but when there is the type of a genuine Tertian, or of one invading every other day, the Bark is as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent now as ever; ſo that 'tis very manifeſt that this Fever was quite different from that of the former Conſtitution, for as much as the uſe of the Bark does now no good, and this is heighthen'd by Wine, Cordials, and other hot things; all which well enough agreed with the uſe of the Bark and alſo with that Fever.</p>
                  <p>Moreover we muſt take notice that this Fever raging all the Summer, eſpecially that of this year, the Diſeaſe did often ſhew it ſelf, not ſo much by the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:153471:44"/>
Pathognomonic ſigns of a Fever, to wit by reſtleſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and inquietude, as by Gripes ſometimes dry and ſometimes looſe, yet notwithſtanding the Fever of this ſeaſon lurk'd under this diſguiſe, in which the inflammatory exhalations of the Blood were not as is uſual protruded to the habit of the Body, but put off inwardly by the Meſenteric Arteries, upon the Viſcera of the lower Belly, and ſometimes upon the Stomach by the branches of the Coeliac Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, which exhalations are wont to provoke Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting, eſpecially preſently after taking Drink or any more ſolid nouriſhment: yet tho this Fever lurk'd under the form of the 'foreſaid Symptoms, yet 'twas to be Cur'd by the genuine Method we deliver'd above, in the ſame manner as if it had appear'd in its own Colours; to wit, by Bleeding and repeated Cathartics; only 'tis to be noted, that when the Fever does ſo much moleſt the Stomach, that it can't retain a Potion, then the Pill <hi>Coch. Major</hi> (of which 2 Scruples preſcrib'd do always paſs through the Body) may be ſubſtituted in the room of a gentle purging Potion; but the Pills muſt be taken at four in the Morning, that the Patient may ſleep after them, and then an Hypnotic in a large doſe is to be allow'd; to wit, a Grain and a half of <hi>Solid London Laudanum,</hi> with the like quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Maſtic made into two Pills, to be taken the ſame Night; or eighteen or twenty drops of <hi>Liquid Laudanum</hi> in an Ounce of <hi>Cinnamon water hordeated</hi> or any other generous Vehicle, by which means the Stomach being both Corroborated, and not Irritated by the ſmall quantity, may not caſt up the Medicine: But if the Purging Potion and Diacodium can poſſibly be retain'd in the Stomach,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:153471:44"/>
they are wholly to be preferr'd before the 'fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Pills and <hi>Laudanum,</hi> for they perform their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs without heating the Body ſo much as the Pills.</p>
                  <p>But ſeeing I have made mention of the Gripes, I will admoniſh my acqaintance with how much danger, as I have frequently obſerv'd, Mineral waters are wont to be preſcrib'd in any Gripes whatever, or Looſneſs, or Vomiting, or any other Diſeaſe whatever, that takes its riſe from a Fever, for as much as in ſo ſubtile and ſpiritual kind of Diſeaſe, as 'tis manifeſt a Fever is, Mineral Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines do ſo confound all things, that inſtead of the Symptoms which were wont to accompany a Fever, they introduce accidents altogether irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, yet in the mean while don't at all aſſiſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the extirpation of the Fever, which I have long and often obſerv'd.</p>
                  <p>But this muſt be ſeriouſly minded, for as much as it may ſerve to deliver many from the Jaws of Death; to wit, that notwithſtanding what we have ſaid before, when the 'foreſaid Gripes riſe to a confirm'd Diſſentery, in which beſides the Gripes ſome Mucous matter together with Blood is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creted by Stool; 'tis manifeſtly very dangerous to treat the Diſeaſe with that tedious Method which orders evacuations firſt, and afterwards thoſe things that attemperate the ſharp Humours (to ſay nothing of Aſtringent Medicines of various kinds and forms, taken inwardly, and Clyſters ſometimes Aſtringent, ſometimes Conſolidating now and then injected) for I have found by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience that a Dyſentery is moſt certainly and moſt ſpeedily Cur'd, if without any more ado the Flux be ſtopt preſently with <hi>Laudanum;</hi> for this Diſeaſe
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:153471:45"/>
is ſo very violent and fierce, that if you perſiſt in Purging, when the Dyſentery is confirm'd, there is great danger, leſt it being heigthen'd by this means ſhou'd by reaſon of its incredible Ferment torment the Patient the ionger, do afterwards what you can, or perhaps kill him. Therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing call'd, I preſently give about twenty two drops of Liquid <hi>Laudanum</hi> in Epidemic water, or in <hi>aq. Mirab.</hi> or the like, to be repeated twice in the ſpace of twenty four hours, or oftner at ſet times, if the Doſe preſcrib'd to be us'd only Morning and Evening, be not ſufficient to quell the Gripes and the Bloody Stools; the Excrements being a little thicken'd, or of a better conſiſtence (which is the firſt ſign of recovery) and the Symptoms being ſubdued, I ſuppoſe its ſafeſt for the Patient to continue a while in the uſe of the 'foreſaid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy Morning and Evening, taking ſome drops dayly till there be no farther occaſion. But 'tis to be noted that I order the Patient to keep his Bed longer after the uſe of a Paregoric, for any Erect poſture ſoon diſturbs the Head unleſs the Patient ſleep long enough after it. As to Diet, if the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient has been accuſtom'd before to Wine, I allow him Canary, but well diluted with water, in which a cruſt of Bread has been boyld, which I order to be kept cold for this uſe in a ſtone bottle, that it may be in readineſs when the Wine is to be attemperated; alſo the white decoction of burnt Harts-horn in Fountain water, drank freely is good; Barly or Chicken-broth, or a poach'd Egg, or any thing elſe of eaſie digeſtion may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for food on the firſt days; but afterwards we muſt riſe by degrees to more generous liquors,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:153471:45"/>
and to a more plentiful and ſolid nouriſhment, leſt too great a vacuity ſhould produce again the ſame Diſeaſe the Patient recover'd of, or ſome other Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptoms that are occaſion'd by emptineſs. But we muſt note this, that tho' Laudanum alone did ſubjugate Dyſentries of this conſtitution, yet in thoſe years in which they are epedimic, and exceed other Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, 'twill not be improper to uſe thoſe evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations firſt, which I have heretofore deſcribed in the Chapter of a Dyſentery.</p>
                  <p>And as in that confirm'd Dyſentery now ſpoke of, ſo in this caſe that follows, it can't be that the Cure ſhould be preſently expedited by that me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod which is proper for the Fever, from whence it firſt took its riſe. For inſtance, ſometimes 'tis ſo that the Patient being ſeiz'd with a horror and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor (heat and cold ſucceeding one another by turns, which are the certain ſigns of an imminent Fever) is of a ſudden miſerably afflicted with the Gripes, by reaſon of an eruption of the febrile matter; and whereas he ought to be purg'd and blooded as directed above: Preſently he betakes himſelf to hot Medicines taken inwardly, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly apply'd, to the intent he may expel the Wind, which he ſuppoſes is the cauſe of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, till at length the pain increaſing, and being as it were impacted into the Bowels by long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, the periſtaltic motion (by which accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Law of Nature, all things ſhou'd be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey'd downwards) begins to be inverted, and all things tend upwards, and the Patient is grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly tormented, and provok'd to vomit, the Diſeaſe now ending in an <hi>Iliac Paſſion.</hi> In this caſe the Phyſician can proceed no further in the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:153471:46"/>
method of Cure, which the Fever, the antecedent cauſe of this Symptom, requir'd, than to order bleeding in the Arm for once: For how many, and whatſoever Catharties you preſcribe, will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently become emetic, and ſo the more promote the inverted motion of the Bowels; for as much as the ſtrongeſt purging Medicines, or indeed the leaſt part of them, can ſcarce paſs the Guts, and cauſe a Stool. In this caſe I think 'tis moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſable, firſt to bleed in the Arm, and an hour or two after to inject a ſtrong Clyſter. I account the ſmoak of Tobacco, ſtrongly blown up through a large Bladder into the Inteſtines by a Pipe invert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to be the beſt and moſt efficacious Clyſter I know, which may be repeated a little while after, unleſs the former, by giving a Stool, open the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages downwards. But this Symptom being not wholly conquer'd by this Remedy, 'tis neceſſary that a Cathartic, ſomewhat ſtronger, be us'd, how difficult ſoever it be to make way.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take of the Pill</hi> ex Duobus <hi>gr.</hi> XXXV. <hi>Mercurius Dulc. one Scruple, make four Pills with a ſufficient quantity of Balſom of</hi> Peru, <hi>take them in a Spoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of Syrup of Violets.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Drink no Liquor upon them, leſt they ſhould not be retain'd; but if the Patient ſhould vomit this Remedy, we muſt proceed in this manner: Let him take preſently 25 drops of Liquid Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danum in half an ounce of ſtrong Cinnamon-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and after a few hours let it be repeated; but when the vomiting and pain of the Belly are aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the uſe of theſe, then the foreſaid Cathartic
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:153471:46"/>
may be repeated again; for at this time 'twill be retained under the protection of the Laudanum, and will at length perform its buſineſs; but if the vomiting and pain ſhould again return, by reaſon the vertue of the Anodyne is wholly decay'd, and the Purge ſhould ſtop in the Body, in this caſe, all hopes from Stools being at preſent laid aſide, we muſt return to the uſe of the Paregoric before deſcrib'd, which muſt be repeated every fourth or ſixth hour, till the Guts be wholly quiet, and the natural motion downwards be reſtor'd, at which time the Cathartic, which has hitherto been ſtopt in the Body, by reaſon of the contrary motion of the Guts, will now operate by Stool; tho' be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the Narcotic ſo often repeated, a quite contrary effect might ſeem to follow, which I have juſt now experienced in a Gentlewoman tormented with a very ſevere <hi>Iliac Paſſion,</hi> who had after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Aphthae</hi> by reaſon of too long retenſion of the humours that occaſion'd the Diſeaſe, and of ſharp Purges; but they were eaſily cur'd by the uſe of the Peruvian Bark above deſcrib'd, and by waſhing the mouth often with the following Gargariſm.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take of Verjuice</hi> 
                     <abbr>lb</abbr> ſſ. <hi>Syrup of Raſberr'ies</hi> ℥i, <hi>make a Gargariſm.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But when theſe paſſages are open again as much as they ſhould be, the Patient may forbear pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging for ſome days, till the Tumult rais'd of late in the Bowels be wholly ceas'd, which ſpace of time may conveniently enough be allow'd for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luting and attemperating the heat and acrimony
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:153471:47"/>
of the humours, which being done, he muſt purge every other day as before, if the leaſt footſteps of the Fever remain: But enough of this.</p>
                  <p>If a Child has this Fever, two Leaches muſt be apply'd behind each Ear, and a Bliſter to the Neck, and it muſt be purged with Beer, wherein Rubarb has been infus'd; if after purging the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſeem to remit, then the Julap muſt be given of the <hi>Cortex Peru,</hi> ſet down for Infants in the Chapter of an intermitting Fever.</p>
                  <p>Moreover 'tis to be noted, that Children are equally obnoxious to this kind of Fever with the Adult, and that therefore they are to be cured by the ſame method, only the quantity of Blood to be taken away, ought to be leſſen'd, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to their Age, and purging ought to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comodated to it, and perchance not ſo often to be us'd; for the Diſeaſes of Infants, and young People will be often tam'd by the firſt or ſecond Purge: Yet we muſt ſeriouſly conſider, whether the Fever treated after this manner, certainly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to this Conſtitution, or to another kind, which ought ſeriouſly to be minded in thoſe Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers that ſeize infants in all conſtitutions of years; for 'tis commonly known, that Children are often ſeiz'd with Fevers, ariſing from their breeding Teeth, which are not eaſily diſtinguiſh'd from Fevers of another kind. I have been in great doubt a long time about the Cure of theſe, neither could I be certainly perſuaded but of late, that any commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to my Care, were recover'd ſo much by Art as by chance; till at length, being frequently admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd of the happy ſucceſs of a Medicine, that is not very famous, yea indeed very contemptible,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:153471:47"/>
upon the account of the common uſe of it; I had alſo preſcrib'd it, which anſwer'd my deſire better than any I know; 'tis three or four drops of Spirit of Hartſhorn, given in a ſpoonful or two of Black cherry-water, or of any other proper Julap, four or ſix times, once every fourth hour</p>
                  <p>There is another Symptom that very much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſts Infants, which is very different from the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, of various conſtitutions of the years, and from that laſt mentioned: 'Tis a ſort of Hectic, that afflicts Children a long time, and thoſe that are troubled with it, languiſh without any conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable heat, with a loſs of Appetite, and a waſting every where, both of the Members and Trunk of the Body. I uſe this simple Method following. Take of choice <hi>Rubarb</hi> flic'd <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ii, let it be put into a glaſs Bottle, containing a Quart of Small Beer, well ſtopt, or any other Liquor the Child uſually drinks of, which medicated Beer I order to be taken both in the day and night, and at meals; which being drank up, I order a quart more to be put upon the ſame <hi>Rubarb,</hi> which alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing drunk off, a quart more is to be put upon it as before, after which the Rubarb commonly loſes its vertue, and the Child recovers; but leſt the Beer firſt put on ſhould be too much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnated with the cathartic quality of the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barb, and ſo purge too much, 'twill be better to add another pint preſently after the firſt is drunk; but afterwards freſh Beer muſt not be added, till the whole Bottle be taken.</p>
                  <p>But to return to the Fever we now treat of, to wit, of the preſent Conſtitution; We muſt dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently obſerve, that in this ſort of Fever (as in a
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:153471:48"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="89" facs="tcp:153471:48"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="90" facs="tcp:153471:49"/>
Rheumatiſm, and many other Diſeaſes, whoſe Cure is perform'd only by evacuations) if we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately inſiſt on the foreſaid evacuations, till all the Symptoms wholly ceaſe, the Sick will often be deſtroy'd; for 'tis not very unuſual that ſome ſlight Symptoms, as it were the reliques of the feeble Fever, remain a while after the Diſeaſe is gon off; yet there is no fear of a relapſe from thence, they retiring gradually, as health returns; for theſe Symptoms are commonly nothing elſe but the true Progeny of thoſe evacuations, by which the Phyſician endeavour'd to cure the Diſeaſe: If this at leaſt be added, as partly the Cauſe, to wit, the emptineſs, that the abſtinence of the Sick from his wonted Meals and Drink has occaſion'd: all which, when they fall upon Bodies weakned, and almoſt worn out by the Diſeaſe, raiſe Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours, as they ſay, as in Women; and for the ſame reaſon, on the account of the weakned, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, and broken Syſtem of the Animal Spirits: Wherefore having made theſe evacuations, that are ſufficient for taking off the Diſeaſe, 'tis the Duty of a prudent Phyſician to forbear the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable adminiſtration of them, and to wait a while on Time, often the beſt and moſt ſucceſsful Phyſician, for the taking off thoſe light Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptoms, which indeed, as I have often obſerv'd, go off at the latter end of ſuch a Diſeaſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any more a-do, by a Paregorick taken at Bed-time two or three nights.</p>
                  <p>The method now deliver'd much excells all I have try'd in the cure of this Fever; and if at any time it does not take it off, yet it forces it to intermit, and then 'tis always cur'd by the Peruvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:153471:49"/>
Bark: But whereas purging, order'd for the cure of this Fever, may perchance ſeem injurious to ſome, I affirm, that upon tryal, nothing ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly and ſo powerfully cools the Patient, as purging preſcrib'd after bleeding, which muſt be always uſed firſt: For tho' a purging does for the preſent raiſe a greater tumult in the Blood, and other humours on the day 'tis taken, and in the operation, than was before, yet that injury will be ſufficiently made up by the advantage that preſently follows; for 'tis found by experience, that purging after bleeding quells a Fever ſooner and better than any other Remedy whatever, both as it expels that filthy humour from the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, by which, as the antecedent Cauſe, the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was occaſion'd; and if they were not pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant before, yet at length being heated, concocted, and thickned by the Fever, do much to render it more laſting: And alſo, as it makes way for an Anodyne, which performs its buſineſs ſafer, and much ſooner, than if the peccant humours, which might otherwiſe hinder the force of the Paregoric, were not eliminated by purging.</p>
                  <p>But on the contrary, as that method which is buſied in eliminating the febrile matter through the pores of the skin be leſs certain, ſo is it more troubleſom and tedious; for by it the Diſeaſe is very often protracted many Weeks, and the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient is brought by this means to the brink of the Grave; and if he chance at length to eſcape Death, he is plagued with a croud of Medicines all the long courſe of the Diſeaſe, to take off thoſe Symptoms, which the ill management of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe brought on, when the Cure of it is attempted
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:153471:50"/>
by the hotteſt method and medicines, which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to its own Genius wholly requires the coldeſt of both; and ſo while brain-ſick men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave themſelves to Rules of Art, falſly ſo call'd, and deſpiſe the judgment of their very Senſes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming them better, they learnedly convert a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, of its own nature ſhort and eaſie, into a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and difficult one, confounding all things through tumult and fear, and raiſing, as they ſay, Waves in a Cup; upon which account there is no more need of them, than of a Pilate, who when he may ſail in the open Sea, ſteers the Ship among Rocks and Shelves; from whence, tho' he may gain an opportunity of acquiring Fame by his great skill in preſerving the Veſſel in ſo great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, yet certainly he will be reckon'd an impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent man.</p>
                  <p>And for theſe Reaſons I can, I truſt, affirm upon good grounds, that the 'foreſaid method of Cure, by bleeding and purging, is more powerful than any other, for the ſubduing of Fevers of moſt kinds; for tho'ſweating, to ſpeak properly, is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures own method, by which ſhe caſts out the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brile matter, and is more genuine and commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous than the reſt, when Nature left to it ſelf, firſt digeſts the 'foreſaid matter, and then when 'tis well concocted, gently expells it through the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit of the Body; which happy event of Nature, of curing Fevers by ſweating, when practical Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans had often obſerv'd, the Dogmatical took occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from hence of making this Rule, That all Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers may, and ought to be cured by this method alone, and no other: But if we ſhould grant this, yet Art, how much ſoever it may ſeem to imitate
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:153471:50"/>
Nature, yet it can't arrogate to it ſelf this privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, that 'tis able to Cure Fevers certainly by Sweating. For firſt Art knows not by what means the peccant matter ſhou'd be fitly prepar'd to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo Expulſion, and if it ſhou'd know this, yet it has no certain ſigns by which it may be admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd of the due preparation of it: ſo that alſo 'tis unavoidably ignorant of the fit time of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking Sweat: and I ſuppoſe no one if he be not very obſtinate, will deny that 'tis very dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to raiſe Sweat raſhly, before a due Concocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for by forcing the crude matter upon the Brain, it adds Oyl to the Flame; and as I have hinted in another place, that that wholeſom ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> (to wit, that things Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocted, not Crude, are to be Medicated) does not ſeem to reſpect ſo much Purging, as Sweat for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by Art. For no one that is but indifferently ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the practice of Phyſick can be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, how many are dangerouſly injur'd by old Women and Quacks, by this prepoſterous uſe of Sudorifics, for 'tis cuſtomary with theſe, if any one complains of Shivering, and a Pain of the Head and Bones, which are moſt commonly the forerunners of a Fever; preſently to put them to Bed, and do all they can to force them to ſweat: by which unſeaſonable endeavours they are ſo far from preventing the Fever, which perchance wou'd go off of its own accord, or by taking away ſome Blood; that on the contrary its the more heigth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en'd, and becomes a confirm'd and radicated Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe. This is moreover to be noted, to ſay no more of old Women, that as thoſe Sweats that come at the beginning of the Fever are wholly Symptoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:153471:51"/>
not Critical, ſo thoſe that are forc'd at the beginning of the Fever by Diaphoretics, moſt commonly conduce no more to the Cure of it than the other Symptomatical Sweats that flow ſo early of their own accord are wont to do, that is, moſt commonly not all; and then as Art is ignorant of the due time for promoting Sweat, ſo likewiſe knows not how long it ſhou'd perſevere in forcing them: for if Sweats are continued beyond the due time by which, to wit, the matter occaſioning the Diſeaſe is wholly expell'd, a Conſumption of thoſe humid Particles, with which the Blood ſhou'd be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted and attemperated, will make the Fever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue longer and heighten it. 'Tis manifeſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore how uncertain this method is, whereas on the contrary 'tis in the Phyſicians power to moderate the other as he pleaſe, in which the Febrile mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is Eliminated by Bleeding and Purging. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over this is to be preferr'd before the other for this reaſon; to wit, that if the Phyſician ſhou'd miſs his aim in Curing the Patient, yet he will not injure him, which is otherwiſe in the uſe of Diaphoretics, unleſs he recover; for the heat of one that is kept continually in Bed, to which he has addicted himſelf for ſome time, contrary to his cuſtom (to ſay nothing of Cordials which are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways us'd in this way of Cure) confounds the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conomy of Nature, and occaſions Convulſions of the Members, and other irregular Symptoms, which can't therefore be deſcrib'd, becauſe they don't belong to the Hiſtory of the Diſeaſe, (which is common in many Symptoms reſpecting all Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes) but take their riſe from the Confuſion and Tumult that are unneceſſarily occaſion'd; by which
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:153471:51"/>
Nature is often oppreſs'd when we carry on the Cure of the Diſeaſe by this Method; all which are commonly wont to be imputed to I know not what Malignity.</p>
                  <p>The invention of which Opinion concerning malignity, either as to the Nameor Notion of it, has been much more deſtructive to mankind than even that of Gunpowder: for as much as thoſe Fevers are chiefly ſaid to be Malignant, in which the inflammation is higher than in others; and therefore Phyſicians have betook themſelves to Cordials and Alexipharmacs, to the end they may expel through the Pores of the Skin the Poyſon they dream of, (for ſo it muſt be call'd, unleſs they had rather trifle about words, than propoſe ſeriouſly that which may be underſtood) upon which account they have preſcrib'd the hotteſt Medicines and Method for thoſe Diſeaſes, which required above others the coldeſt Remedies and Regimen, which is manifeſt enough both in the Small Pox, (which is one of the hotteſt Diſeaſes in Nature) and in the Cure of other Fevers: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which Error perchance they were led, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the Petechiae and purple ſpots, and other Phaenomena of the ſame kind, all which owe their riſe in moſt Subjects to an Inflammation ſuperin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd upon the Blood of the Patient, too much fired by the Fever already; for as much as they rarely happen, except at the beginning of the Plague, and of thoſe Flux-Small Pox that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate of the higheſt Inflammation: for in this kind of Diſeaſe the Livid Spots appear in va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious parts of the Body, together with the Puſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, when they firſt come out, and the Patient will
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:153471:52"/>
be troubled with an Excretion of Blood, either by the Urinary paſſages, or by the Lungs, with a Cough, when the Blood rages with ſuch a violent motion and fury occaſion'd by the Inflammation, that having broke through all, it ruſhes into the Cavities of the Body. And tho the Purple Spots in this Fever don't take their riſe from ſuch an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe heat of the Blood, as that is which cauſes ſuch Haemorrhages, yet notwithſtanding they are produced by the ſame Inflammation, tho in a leſs degree; and when there is not that Execretion of Blood they are eaſily taken off by a cooling Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. But if they conjecture there is Malignity in the caſe, not only from the Purple Spots, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo becauſe they have obſerv'd that the Symptoms of the Fever have been ſometimes milder than may ſeem to agree with the Nature of it, and yet that the Patient was more weaken'd than cou'd be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected in the time he has been ill: I anſwer, that all theſe things proceed only from hence, <hi>viz.</hi> for that Nature being as it were oppreſs'd and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd by the firſt aſſault of the Diſeaſe, is not able to raiſe regular Symptoms, and ſuch as are agreeable to the greatneſs of the Diſeaſe, but all the <hi>Phaenomena</hi> are wholly irregular; for the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Economy being diſturb'd, and as it were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, the Fever on that account is depreſs'd, which according to the genuine courſe of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture us'd to be high. Of which, I remember, I ſaw a notable experiment many years ago, in a young Man to whom I was call'd; for tho he ſeem'd almoſt dying, yet the heat in the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal parts of the Body felt ſo temperate upon touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the ſtanders by wou'd not believe me
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:153471:52"/>
when I affirm'd that he had a Fever, which by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the oppreſſion of the Blood (by whoſe bulk it was kept in and as it were choak'd) cou'd not extricate and ſhew it ſelf openly: but that if they let him Blood they ſhou'd preſently perceive the Fever high enough, a Vein being open'd and a pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty deal of Blood taken away, the Fever broke out, which was as violent as I ever ſaw any, and did not go off till bleeding had been us'd three or four times.</p>
                  <p>But if the A rguments I have brought are not ſo conſiderable as to prove the thing certainly to be, as I ſay, yet if I find by experience that this Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver does not go off eaſily by Evacuations, made by Sweat, I have what I ſeek for: For no Man can tell by arguing, but by experience, what kind of Fever can and ought to be Cur'd by Sweats, and what by other Evacuations. And truly no wiſe Man, who has ſufficiently weigh'd the nature of Men and things, can implicitly believe the Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any Man, how great ſoever he be, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning thoſe things that are meer Speculations, and can't be determin'd by any certain Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for he ought to conſider that the moments of reaſon are ſo very various and ſubtile, that when any one has propos'd a Speculation, ſo eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by firm Reaſons, that he forces the aſſent of all that are near him; preſently another ſucceeds him, endow'd perchance with better Parts, who confutes that Opinion which was ſo fairly ſettl'd, and clearly proves by a ſtronger force of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that that was nothing but a fiction of the Brain, for as much as not the leaſt Footſteps of it
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:153471:53"/>
are to be found in Nature; and in the room of it ſubſtitutes a certain new Hypotheſis more proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble than the former and more neatly contriv'd, yet this latter Fiction undergoes the ſame fate with the former, when ſome third perſon oppoſes, who as much exceeds the ſecond in Ingenuity as he did the firſt; and ſo there will be no end till at length we come to him that is arriv'd at the top of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Ingenuity; and how difficult it is to find this Man, and to know him from others, any one will preſently perceive who is not ſo very mad as to arrogate this praiſe to himſelf. For as we may conjecture that there are almoſt infinite Natures in the illuſtrious Orbs, here and there ſcatter'd throug the Firmament of the Univerſe, endow'd with far more excellent Intellects than weak Man; ſo we don't certainly know whether mankinds Brain, the Shop of the Thoughts, be not ſo form'd by Nature, that they can't find ſo well what is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely true, as what is moſt convenient and ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to their Natures. And ſo much may ſuffice to be ſpoken to thoſe, who in Phyſick truſt more to vain Speculations than to Experience, built upon the ſolid teſtimony of the Senſes.</p>
                  <p>But if any one ſhou'd here object, and ſay, don't we ſee <hi>de facto</hi> that this Fever is very often Cur'd by a method quite contrary to this you deliver? I Anſwer, That the Cure of the Diſeaſe, which only the recovery of a Patient now and then wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes for, wholly differs from the Cure of the ſame, by that Method of Practiſe which is confirm'd by more frequent recoveries of the Sick, and all other Practical <hi>Phanomena</hi> that happen in the Cure of it.
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:153471:53"/>
For inſtance in the Small Pox, many who have been tormented with the cruel uſe of a hot Regimen, and Medicines have yet recover'd; and on the contrary they have done very well, whoſe Cure has been perform'd by a Method quite contrary. Now how ſhall we end this ſtrife, which Method is to be preferr'd? Why truly by this means we ſhall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly judge: namely, if I have found in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Method, that the more I have heated the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, the more I have rais'd and promoted the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, reſtleſsneſs, the Delirium, and other Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptoms: and on the contrary, if it appears, that when he has been moderately cool'd, his tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is ſo much the more Sedate, and he is the leſs vex'd with the Fever and other Symptoms. Moreover that by keeping that due temper of the Muſcular parts, which beſt ſuits with the increaſe and maturation of the Piſtules, they are bigger and more fill'd than if the Patient were ſuffocated with too much heat. The caſe being thus put, I ſuppoſe 'tis manifeſt enough which Method of Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe we ought rather to follow. In like manner if I find in the Fever I now Treat of, that the more the Patient is heated, the more he is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd not only to a Phrenſie, Purple Spots, <hi>Petechiae</hi> and the like; but that 'tis moreover on that account encompaſs'd with irregular and anomalous Symptoms of all ſorts; and on the other Hand, if I obſerve another Patient treated by the Method we now propoſe, wholly freed from theſe Symptoms, Reaſon dictates that the latter Method of Practiſe, is much to be preferr'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the other, tho both Patients recover by ſuch
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:153471:54"/>
different means; but if more eſcape Death by this way than the other, the intricaſie of the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie is ſo much the eaſier found out; but I muſt not judge of this, leſt I ſhould favour too much my own Opinion.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:153471:54"/>
            <list>
               <head>The CONTENTS of the Second Part.</head>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. I.</label>
A <hi>Continual Epidemic Fever, of a new kind, began to rage together with other Inflammatory Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes,</hi> Page 1, 2. <hi>It's Diagnoſtic ſigns,</hi> ibid. <hi>The Looſneſs which; as we ſaid, was Cured in the former Fever by a Vomit was highthen'd by the ſame in this,</hi> ibid. <hi>The Plague raged violently, the various ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of it,</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. II.</label>
                  <hi>The Symptoms of ſome Fevers which are Vulgarly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Malignant, are not ſo in their own Natures, but proceed from the ill management of the Cure,</hi> page 3. <hi>A Fever truly Malignant is of the ſame ſpecies of the Plague and only differs in degree,</hi> ib. <hi>The ſmall Pox and the Plague ſhew that Epidemic Diſeaſes proceed from the various Craſis of the Air,</hi> p. 3. 4. <hi>But what that is we know not,</hi> ib. <hi>The Plague ſeldom happens in</hi> England <hi>oftner than once in about forty years,</hi> ibid. <hi>Fevers that rage a year or two after a dreadful Plague are Peſtilential, and require the ſame Method of Cure,</hi> ibid. <hi>Beſides the diſpoſition of the Air there is required a Fomes of the Venom to occaſion the Plague, tranſmitted either mediately or immediately from ſome Plaguy Body,</hi> p. 4. &amp; 5. <hi>'Tis propagated by the infected Air,</hi> ib. <hi>When it's Epidemical it begins between Spring and
<pb facs="tcp:153471:55"/>
Summer,</hi> ibid. <hi>And ſeldom at any other time, the the diſpoſition of the Air be Peſtilential, yet it tis not ſufficient of it ſelf to cauſe the Plague,</hi> p. 6. <hi>neither will the Plague be Epidemical unleſs there be a ſuitable diſpoſition of the Air,</hi> ibid. <hi>The man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of it's invaſion is deſcribed,</hi> ibid. <hi>Sudden Death ſeldom happens unleſs at the beginning of a ſweeping Plague,</hi> p. 7. <hi>They that have Tumours without a Fever or any great Symptom have no need of a Method of Cure,</hi> ibid. <hi>The Eſſence of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, even as of Animals and Vegetables is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether unknown to us,</hi> ibid. <hi>The Cure of moſt Diſeaſes is not accompliſhed by the knowledge of their Cauſes, but by a Method approved by experience,</hi> pag. 8. <hi>The Plague is a Fever of it's own kind taking it's riſe from an Inflammation of the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous particles of the Blood,</hi> ibid. <hi>Peſtilential Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers proceed from a more remiſs Inflammation,</hi> p. 9. <hi>An Eriſipilas is like the Plague,</hi> ibid. <hi>That the Plague ariſes from an Inflammation may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by many arguments,</hi> p. 10. <hi>Alexipharmacs and other hot Medicines do only good by accident</hi> (viz.) <hi>as they are Diaphoretics,</hi> p. 11. <hi>It's probable that Wine drank too freely, and hot Antidotes have brought the Plague upon many,</hi> ibid. <hi>In the Cure of the Plague we either ſuccour Nature by follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her conduct, or by ſubſtituting another more ſafe that is contrary to her's,</hi> p. 12. <hi>Alexiphar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mac's in this and other Diſeaſes ſeem to do good, rather by cauſing ſome Evacuation than by any ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cific vertue,</hi> ibid. <hi>The Plague according to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures cuſtom ſeems chiefly to be carried off by Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes in the Emunctories, a Peſtilential Fever by Sweat,</hi> p. 13. <hi>Therefore there muſt be a different
<pb facs="tcp:153471:55"/>
Method in theſe Diſeaſes,</hi> ibid. <hi>Sweats raiſed in the Plague are ſometimes deadly,</hi> p. 14. <hi>They of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten hinder the Irruption of the Bubo by diſſipating the matter otherwhere,</hi> ibid. <hi>The Phiſician is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to follow Natures guidance in other Diſeaſes, but to renounce it in the Plague,</hi> p. 15. <hi>It ſeems the Plague muſt be conquered either by Bleeding or Sweat,</hi> ibid. <hi>Large Bleeding repeated was never mortal to any before the Tumour broke out,</hi> p. 16. <hi>The reaſon why ſparing Phlebotomy, or when the Tumour's out ſhould be always hurtful,</hi> ibid. <hi>That Bleeding is ſafer than all other Remedies in the Plague, is clearly proved by</hi> Botallus <hi>in a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of inſtances,</hi> p. 17. <hi>This is confirmed by a wonderful Obſervation amongſt us,</hi> p. 18. <hi>For what reaſon the Diſſipation of the Peſtilential fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by Sweat, is to be preferred before Bleeding,</hi> p. 19. <hi>What difficulties tis accompanied with,</hi> ibid. <hi>Plaguy Tokens ſeem to ariſe from a Diſſolution of the Sanguineous Fibres not unlike ſtripes inflicted by a violent blow,</hi> ibid. <hi>Sweat being broke off too ſoon, either the Buboes coming out go back or never attain to legitimate abceſſes,</hi> pag. 20. <hi>Continual Fevers about the end of Spring and the beginning of Summer, readily turn either to Agues or Pluriſies, or other Diſeaſes of the Inflammatory kind,</hi> p. 21. <hi>For what reaſon the Author was forced to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive another Method for this new Fever different from that which hitherto he had uſed with good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs,</hi> p. 23. <hi>The Author Cured the Peſtilential Fever by Bleeding repeated,</hi> ibid. <hi>Blood is to be taken away in a ſufficient quantity or not at all,</hi> p. 24. <hi>What Method the Author ſubſtituted in the room of the former,</hi> p. 25. <hi>Bleeding before Sweat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:153471:56"/>
expedites it and makes it more ſafe,</hi> ibid. <hi>The covering of the head conduces much to the raiſing of Sweat,</hi> ibid. <hi>As ſoon as the rays of the Morbific matter tend towards the ſurface of the Body, the Looſneſs and Vomiting occaſioned by them ſtop of their own accord,</hi> p. 26. <hi>The Sweat muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued by the ſpace of a Natural day,</hi> ibid. <hi>You muſt take great care the Patient be not cleanſed nor that the Shirt be changed till twenty four hours after the end of the Sweat,</hi> p. 26. 27. <hi>If the Sweat is broke off too ſoon, the fury of the Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptoms will preſently return,</hi> ibid. Diemerbrookes <hi>objection againſt long Sweats is anſwered,</hi> ibid. <hi>It's mad appear that the Patient is not weakned, but rather ſtrengthened thereby,</hi> ibid. <hi>When the Sweat is at hight the Patient may be refreſhed with comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Broths,</hi> p. 28. <hi>A Purge muſt be given the next day,</hi> ibid. <hi>The wonderful ſucceſs of this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod in the Peſtilential Fever,</hi> ibid. <hi>The Author did not dare to Bleed when the Tumour was out,</hi> ibid. <hi>By what means it ſeems it may be ſafely tryed,</hi> p. 29.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:153471:56"/>
               <head>The CONTENTS of the Third Part.</head>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. I.</label>
                  <hi>THE Febrile commotion of the Blood is intended for the Secretion of ſome Heterogeneous matter, or for changing the diſpoſition of the Blood,</hi> Page 31. <hi>In both caſes 'tis chiefly indicated, that the Blood be contained within the bounds that are agreeable to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures purpoſs,</hi> p. 34. <hi>To whom Bleeding is hurtful,</hi> ib. <hi>For whom 'tis uſeful,</hi> p. 35. <hi>Who ought to take a Vomit, who ought not,</hi> ibid. <hi>If it be omitted when 'tis indicated a Looſneſs follows,</hi> p. 36. <hi>But not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in Malignant Fevers,</hi> ibid. <hi>Why this Looſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is ſo dangerous,</hi> ibid. <hi>'Tis preſently ſtopt by a Vomit not by Aſtringent Medicines,</hi> p. 36. 37. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timonial Vomits are dangerous unleſs they are well waſh'd off,</hi> ibid. <hi>Where Bleeding and Vomiting are both requir'd, Bleeding is to precede,</hi> ibid. <hi>After the Vomit an Anodine muſt be given at bed time,</hi> p. 39. <hi>'Tis not ſafe to give a Vomit of</hi> Crocus Metallorum <hi>to any under fourteen,</hi> p. 40. <hi>The heat of the Blood is ſometimes to be bridled by Bleeding, ſometimes by Clyſters injected every other day,</hi> p. 41. <hi>For whom Cordials are proper, and at what time of the Diſeaſe,</hi> p. 43. 44. <hi>Cooling Medicines given after the fourteenth day do hurt,</hi> ibid. <hi>Moderate Cordials are to be given at the beginning, and hotter according to the progreſs of the Diſeaſe,</hi> p. 45. <hi>Forms of Cordials,</hi> p. 46. <hi>Purging Potion is to be given on the fifteenth day,</hi> p. 48. <hi>The omiſſion of
<pb facs="tcp:153471:57"/>
Purging after Autumnal Diſeaſes has occaſion'd many others,</hi> ibid. <hi>Sometimes the Purge is to be put off till the ſeventeenth day,</hi> p. 49. <hi>The Diet and Regimen of thoſe that are recovering,</hi> ibid. <hi>Old Malago or the like is proper for old People at the end of the Diſeaſe, to Expectorate the viſcous Phlegm,</hi> p. 50. <hi>Cooling Medicines and Clyſters given too late, especially in old People, retarde the Despumati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Morbific matters,</hi> p. 51. <hi>How a Phrenſie and Watchings are to be manag'd,</hi> p. 53. <hi>Anodynes are not proper when the Fever is at height, but are us'd ſucceſsfully at the latter end of the Diſeaſe,</hi> ibid. <hi>If it can be, the Patient ſhou'd be purg'd before he uſe the Anodyne,</hi> p. 55. <hi>Oyl of Almonds is beſt in the Cough,</hi> p. 56. <hi>An Haemorrhage of the Noſe is ſometimes to be permitted,</hi> p. 58. <hi>The Patient muſt be Purg'd after an immoderate Haemorrhage,</hi> ibid. <hi>A large doſe of Diaſcordium is better for ſtoping the Hickocks than any Specific whatever,</hi> p. 59. <hi>If a Looſneſs come, tho a Vomit has been given, an aſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Clyſter muſt be injected,</hi> ibid. <hi>The cauſe of the Iliac paſſion,</hi> p. 62. <hi>The uſe of Quickſilver and Bullets do little good in the Iliac Paſſion, and often hurt,</hi> p. 63. <hi>The Cure of it,</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>CHAP. II.</label>
                  <hi>The new Fever began in February,</hi> 84/5. <hi>'twas more Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demic in other places than in</hi> London, page 66. 67. <hi>The Symptoms of this Fever,</hi> ibid. <hi>The Inclination in this Fever to a Frenſie is very great,</hi> p. 68. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiae very often break out by reaſon of the unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable uſe of Cordials and too hot a Regimen,</hi> ibid. <hi>Sweat forc'd by art at the beginning of the Diſeaſe us'd to put off the Morbific matter either on the
<pb facs="tcp:153471:57"/>
Head or Limbs,</hi> p. 69. <hi>The Method of Cure,</hi> p. 70, 71, 72, 73. <hi>Spirit of Vitriol is not proper in any Diſeaſes that are Cur'd by Purging,</hi> ibid. <hi>The gentle heat of the bed a nights opportunely ſavours ſuch Sweats as flow of their own accord in the night,</hi> p. 74. <hi>The Diet,</hi> ibid. <hi>'Tis not neceſſary to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid the eating of Chickens and the like of eaſie Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction after the taking of two Purges,</hi> p. 74, 75. <hi>Three or four ſpoonfuls of Canary Wine may be taken night and morning, and after dinner for ſome days after the laſt Purge if the Fever has a little ſpent it ſelf and is not yet turn'd to an Ague,</hi> ibid. <hi>The Patient muſt lye a bed only a nights,</hi> ibid. <hi>Of the Coma that comes upon this Fever,</hi> p. 76. <hi>If there be Convulſive motions of the Body the Phyſitian muſt not be deterr'd from making the 'foreſaid evacuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> p. 77. <hi>Of the Convulſion call'd</hi> Chorea Sancti Viti, ibid. <hi>The Cure of it,</hi> p. 78. <hi>How Hyſterical Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that have this Fever are to be treated,</hi> p. 80. <hi>This Fever had an Exacerbation daily about night, not much unlike the fit of an Ague,</hi> p. 81. <hi>The Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver lurk'd under the form of the Gripes,</hi> p. 82. <hi>The Method of Cure in this caſe,</hi> ibid. <hi>Mineral Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are not proper in any Diſeaſe that takes its riſe from a Fever,</hi> p. 83. <hi>How the Patient muſt be manag'd if the Gripes turn to a Dyſentery,</hi> p. 83, 84. <hi>How the Patient is to be manag'd when the Gripes turn to an Iliac Paſſion,</hi> p. 85, 86, 87. <hi>The Cure of the Aphthae,</hi> ibid. <hi>How Infants are to be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nag'd in this Fever,</hi> ibid. <hi>The Cure of the Fever ariſing from breeding of Teeth,</hi> p. 88, 89. <hi>Of the Cure of the Hectic peculiar to Children,</hi> ibid. <hi>The ſlight Symptoms that remain after the Diſeaſe is gone off will be Cur'd by time,</hi> p. 90.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:153471:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
